He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made
by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers and giant killer,
but it's easy for me to say,
giant killers, dragon slayers, it's a giant killers.
I think that becomes a football thing, then.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen D'Young is with me
from Lafayette, Louisiana,
and I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
We are recording live but we're actually
not going to be taking phone calls tonight.
That said, if you leave a question on our Facebook or ancient faith YouTube streams
and we spot it, there is a chance that we could take it and respond.
Anyway, let's dive in.
So are you ready, Father Steven?
Yes.
All right.
This is going to be an all Q&A episode, everybody.
So we got piles and piles of questions from you.
Lots were sent by email, but then also...
or a lot were sent by voicemail.
And since we got plenty of the voicemail variety,
we're favoring that.
Number one, because we love to hear your wonderful voices.
But number two, it just makes for better radio actually.
But so don't be discouraged though.
We still want to hear from you by email.
You're welcome to send that in.
But we, like I said, voicemail is better.
So here we are.
Lots and lots of questions today.
So I'm just gonna start us off with the first one.
this one comes from actually my old seminary class.
made Father Christopher.
Leviticus chapter 18 deals with various and sundry forms of sexual immorality that the
Lord commands the children of Israel not to do according to the way of life in the land
of Egypt and Canaan, because this way of life vexes the land itself.
one verse in this chapter stands out as very different.
And
On first reading, it doesn't look like it's dealing with sexual immorality, and that's verse 21.
Furthermore, you shall not give your offspring to worship a ruler, nor shall you defile my holy name. I am the Lord.
My question is, is this verse
actually talking about the Nephilim ritual?
Thank you, fathers.
There you go right out of the gate with a giant question.
Yay.
So
I don't you know my I didn't think the question was that long. Oh wait you meant the other way.
All right, so a good pun pun to start off with. Yeah, punishment continued as it will.
It will continue no matter how morale does.
I mean, like my read on where he says not give your offspring to worship a ruler. I mean,
I mean, ruler there, right, that's referring to gods, right?
Is that the idea?
It's not talking about...
Well, of course, you know, you're local.
You're local God King is a God, right?
It's it's kind of a mis-translation.
Oh, well right.
Take his in.
Yeah, well, it's Molek.
That was that what it says literally is Molek.
Yeah, and and someone read Molek as Melak, which means King.
Wow.
All right.
Is that, I mean, I don't have my sub, you know, my sub-tourage in front of me.
Is that the sub-tourage at reading?
Is that it?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So so don't give your kids to Molek who is the
Notorious specific demon. Yeah, yeah
So I mean their business derived it's it's derived from the
Same route right the same way that like bail right Paul means master or lord right right?
Right, Molek kind of means ruler. So it's like kind of a mistranslator
Yeah, then it's not translated as a proper noun
Yeah, and you know notoriously, Mola is the
one associate with child sacrifice in the Old Testament, right?
Right.
Yeah.
So probably not referencing the Nephilim ritual, but really talking about sacrificing children
to this demon.
Right.
And the connection to the sexual immorality element is that this is related to fertility,
right?
Hmm.
So people would sacrifice a child to molac the idea being that would guarantee
fertility and you'd have a bunch more children. Oh wow.
Counterintuitive, I know. I mean, there's a weird parallel there to the whole prosperity gospel seed
faith thing. You know, right. Pay this money and you'll get a lot more money later.
Yeah, right. There's a little darker. Yes, wait. Yeah.
Yeah, like I don't think Ron Parsley sacrificed any babies, but
Good old information. I don't let the police know, but I'm pretty sure he's not.
Yeah, so but yeah, that's so that's the connection, right? That's the connection. Yeah, and a lot of the
The commandments that are in Leviticus 18 are bluntly talking about non-reproductive.
sex. Yeah, all sterile kinds of things that are against the basic commandment of B fruitful.
Right, and so this is related to that, and they're all directed toward men because, of course,
women at that time did not have the right of consent, so it was men making the decisions about
these things. Yeah. And so it's restricting male sexuality from these various outlets, right?
because men...
for some reason in the past,
wanted to have a lot of sex without having a lot of children,
they'd have to be responsible for it.
Ha.
Yeah, co-figure.
Yeah.
And also, I mean, the pairing of idolatry
and sexual emerality is ubiquitous in the Bible, right?
I mean, everywhere.
Yeah.
Right.
Alright
Well, moving on to our next question for this first half.
This one is from Noah.
Hello, fathers.
I was wondering, what is the on theological significance
of the fact that in John's gospel,
Jesus doesn't exercise any demons,
even though he's seen doing this in the other three?
Thanks.
Yes, so I mean, number one,
there's a lot of differences between John's gospel
and the synoptic gospel's Matthew, Mark, and Luke.
Why is this? It's funny.
actually I had never noticed this before but then when we got this question I kind of looked it up and I was like,
oh hey that's that's right I don't I can't remember any exorcisms and Johns-Calls won't can't find any.
Is that true? Are there not any?
And if not why why do you think that would not be in the picture there?
So I have said that there aren't any in your presence before so I'll care.
Oh really? I can't remember any out a lot of it.
Everything you say, you say a lot of things.
It's true, but I also repeat myself a lot.
That's true to the flip side of the flip side. I say the same things over and over again a lot of time. Yeah
But it is true that there are no exorcisms in say John's gospel. I mean on one hand
This is kind of an unanswerable question in that you have to get into sick John's head and say hey, why did you put in any exorcism?
But I'm not just gonna say that
I
personally hold to and I think there's good warrant for this. I mean, it's an orthodox Christian,
the iconography of St. John, composing his gospel with a scribe. Always depicts him as an elderly man,
for example. And so based on sort of everything the fathers say, all the traditions of the church,
Rather than my own conjecture, I'll leave that.
That is St. John's Gospel.
it in the last. Right. And there's been some good scholarly work published in the last
several years in Johanine studies that makes a really good case that not only is St. John's
Gospel written after the Sinoptic Gospels, the other three, but that it is aware of the
Yeah, right so he's like well look you guys got this
covered. So I'm going to focus on this over here. Right. And there are places where he seems
to be deliberately filling in gaps. Right. So for example, talking about the raising of Lazarus,
it's a direct connection to Christ's triumphal entry on Paul's side. Yeah, big example. Because
I mean, the raising of Lazarus isn't even in the other three, right? Right. We just see all these
people excited to see Jesus. Right? Yeah, it comes out of the blue. Yeah. Oh.
Well, here he is.
Welcome, big crowds and pom branches and like, wait, who is this guy again?
I mean, it doesn't quite make sense in those gospels.
But if you, you know, if Word has gotten out that he raised this guy four days dead out
of the tomb, people are going to turn out for that.
You know, they're going to want to see this guy who can do that because no one's ever even
heard of that before.
Right.
And so there are a bunch of other examples besides the exorcism also.
For example,
St. John's Gospel doesn't have the institution of the Eucharist.
It has the footwashing and then it sort of skips.
It has the footwashing that the other Gospels don't.
And then it has a much more elaborated sort of final discourse of Christ to his disciples,
after the mystical suffer.
But it doesn't describe the institution of the Eucharist.
you have John 6 which isn't.
That whole discourse is not in the other gospels.
You have that talking about the Eucharist, but you don't have the actual institution.
The weirdest one of these though is that technically Jesus doesn't get baptized in Satan, John
is fasting.
Because it describes him coming to Saint John the Forerunner and then it skips to when
he came up out of the water.
Yeah, it's gives the actual baptism.
parts. In the same way it skips the institution of the Eucharist. So in a lot of ways, John's gospel
functions as a kind of theological supplement to the other three. Right. Yeah. Right. And so it
takes for granted, like in those cases, literally takes for granted that you're aware of the
contents of the others. Yeah. And so he can fill things in. He can talk about things that
maybe he was privy to the other gospel, right?
weren't, right? And sort of expand on some of those things without having to just go through the same
material again. And then the other three, I mean, you know, without getting into the weeds of
whether, you know, one of them is used as a source for the others or whatever. The way they
They just pick and fights.
I'm just letting you know I'm aware of that.
OK.
They don't they don't function.
this way there's not like, well, you know, look, Mark had this covered so I don't really need to include like there's they don't reference. Yeah, they seem to function as units on their own on some, you know, like they're, they're, you know, they're trying to be complete.
According to that particular author's vision for what a complete gospel looks like, you know, right.
I mean, St. Luke at the beginning of his gospel makes the reference to a bunch of people.
people having written things before.
Right.
But other than that, right,
he makes that sort of general reference
the fact that I'm using source material.
Right.
But other than that, there's a specific,
like I got this from this person,
I got this from that person.
Yeah.
There's some hints at that in St. Luke's Gospel
in that he will sometimes name the people
for like no particular reason.
Hmm.
He'll say, this was so and so,
you know, the son of so and so,
or someone's other brother or someone's other.
right, which kind of implies that maybe who he talked to.
Yeah.
And you just sort of assumes that the people who are his original readers at least will know
who that is or be able to ask them something or whatever, right?
Yeah.
But yeah, beyond that, there aren't like, he doesn't say like, as St. Mark wrote.
Right, right, exactly.
And you know, of course, when you're talking about the two of them in particular, they were
not present for the vast
of what they're writing about.
So they're all getting that from other sources.
You know, they're talking to people
and maybe there is some other stuff written down
that we don't have.
But-
Say Mark's getting it traditionally from St. Peter, yeah.
Yeah, right, right, very interesting.
All right, well, so the answer knows,
we don't really quite know exactly
what their architecture systems in John's Gospel,
but maybe he figured that had been taking care of already,
you know, by the way.
But good catch, but yeah, I mean,
it's so prominent in the other three
that he may have felt with that.
Sure, right?
As he seems to have with some other things.
Yeah, exactly.
OK.
All right.
We got one from Jesse who has a question
about Holy Spirit Procession.
Hello, fathers.
This is Jesse Cosby.
I have a question about prophecy.
As I've been listening to Lord of Spirits
and my understanding of what prophecy is
and the role that it plays in scripture
and in our lives has been expanded.
I'm a little...
confused about certain areas of scripture where it talks about the Holy Spirit coming
upon someone and they begin to prophesy. Almost in an uncontrolled way, I mean probably
the most obvious example would be Saul when the Holy Spirit comes on him when he's coming
to attack David and he begins prophesying and takes all of his clothes off and it's almost
like he's acting as if he has no control on his madman.
to be something that we would associate with demonic possession, not the
the Holy Spirit. And we're never really told what they say. So I'm wondering what
does prophecy in this sense look like? What are they saying? What exactly are
they? Are they just praising God? Are they speaking about something that's going
to happen? Like I'm trying to understand how to read these portions of scripture.
Thank you so much.
question. I mean, it's notable, and you've pointed this out before, that there are, it's
not just like with Saul suddenly, you know, jerking around on the ground, you know. But
like there are other cases where it seems like the Holy Spirit sort of takes hold of someone
and kind of on some level makes them do something. Right. I mean, what are the conditions?
Why would he do that? I mean, obviously we cannot know the mind of God. But you know, I'm
Like there are clearly times when prophecy seems to be a...
That's more kind of synergistic thing.
You know, like I heard the word of the Lord, or I saw him and he said this to me, and now
I'm passing this on to you.
It doesn't seem like there's no point where the Holy Spirit functions as a kind of, you
know, functions through someone in a kind of a regular way that I can recall.
Am I forgetting something?
But there are moments that he grabs hold of people.
things happen, right?
Right.
Yeah.
Most of the time when you see the phenomenon of holy spirit possession, whoever gets sort
of possessed, kills a whole lot of people.
I'll just even problematize it even more.
Like it judges and it Joshua.
That's like that literally happens.
It always spirit came upon somebody like Samson.
People love what I talk about Samson and you know he kills hundreds of people.
Right.
notice that the language seems to be different.
Like the spirit comes upon versus someone is filled with the Holy Spirit.
Is that a real distinction? Right, comes upon and then departs.
Right? Whereas when St. Stephen, when he's about to be martyred,
you know, is said to be filled with the Holy Spirit and then he speaks.
Right. Right. Where that sort of a quality of him,
Right, that he's been filled with the Spirit, whereas...
And like the Samson case or one of the other judges case, it's the Holy Spirit just comes upon him sort of seasons him does this at the departments, right?
We don't get the idea that the Holy Spirit sort of rushed upon St Stephen and then left.
Yeah.
Right, quite the opposite.
Right.
He's filled with the Holy Spirit.
I mean, this is who he is, you know, but this is a kind of a peaking sort of speak, right?
Right.
Yeah.
And, and yes, prophecy is usually, as you said, kind of synergistic, right?
Because we see prophets who sort of cooperate and we see like Jonah who kind of does
a cooperate.
Right, right.
He's like most of the book.
Yeah, although in, you know, in, in his case, still like the Holy Spirit doesn't grab
hold of him, he just has given so many opportunities for repentance.
Yeah, finally does.
Yeah, that he finally sort of cooperates and that has been her about it.
Yeah.
So, yeah, so we have to remember that the Holy Spirit, the way the Holy Spirit is talked about,
let me say this is especially clear in the Old Testament. This is part of why we sometimes miss it,
is as like the presence of God who's filling the tabernacle of the temple.
Right, so it's presence of God himself because the Holy Spirit is God. Right, but it's sort of filling.
presence very much has this ambivalent nature.
right? In the sense that this is a blessing for Israel, right? The God has come to dwell with them.
It's also dangerous. You have the whole death by holiness thing, right? That is a potential there,
right? And so the way that that goes, whether it goes one way or the other in terms of the
presence of God is based on the holiness or the corruption, the purity or impurity of...
the person encountering the presence of God.
Yeah, spirit.
Right. And so a person who has repented, who's been made clean, right?
That's why Isaiah, look at the calling of Isaiah, right? Isaiah comes into the presence of God,
immediately like, woe is me, we'll say. Right?
The King James is like, woe is me, it is undone, right? It's the equivalent of person.
Right, he's like, I'm done.
Right? Right? Because of his own sinfulness. And then there's this symbolic purification
with the coal. Yeah. Right? And then after the purification, he's then able to receive
and go on this mission. Right? So the negative reaction, we see a negative reaction like
Saul, right? Saul at this point has an unclean spirit dwelling within him. Right. Right.
and is out for murder out of his own jealous, right?
And anger.
And so when he comes into the presence of God,
that's not a good experience.
Right.
It's not death exactly by holiness,
but getting there, right?
It's sort of torture by holiness, right?
Madness as a result of it.
Yeah.
Right.
And so we don't obviously know the exact words
that we're coming out of his mouth.
Right.
But, you know...
we should think about, for example, when we're told that ultimately every knee
will bow in heaven and on earth and under the earth. So including the devil and
confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, that's not going to be a pleasurable experience.
Right? Right?
A devil to speak that truth. Right? So even prophecy is not necessarily
a pleasurable experience.
when you see somebody getting seized by the Holy Spirit and the Holy Spirit departing like that,
it's because that person themselves has not been sort of pure. Like God is doing is will through them.
But the Holy Spirit can't abide there because it has been purified. So that's as we come up,
as we record this, we're coming up on Pentecost. So this chain that Saint Luke makes between the
It's the perfect.
of the world and of humanity by Christ's blood on the cross, then allows the Holy Spirit to come
in dwell within people, right, continually, right? That connection is there. Otherwise, the Holy
Spirit couldn't because it would kill us. Yeah, right. You know, the other takeaway I have from this
is that just because God makes use of someone doesn't mean that they are a saint, that they have to
to be a bad...
or whatever, you know, there's that whole, like within certain sectors of Christianity,
that whole touch not the Lord's anointed kind of thing, which is basically a way for allowing
abusive church leaders to continue to not face any consequences, you know, like look
at his success, how can you possibly criticize him, you know, like, well, actually.
Yeah, right. Right. Exactly. Okay. You can apply that literally. I mean, you shouldn't go around
killing those people. Yes. That's what it meant. That was David Refusing to actually
Thank you.
murder assault. Yes, sir. There we go. Yes, but you should not do that. But killing the worst
pastor. Yeah, you should not murder them and take over. Yes, exactly. You're serving a kingdom,
killing a pastor is not the same thing as criticizing him for bad things he's done or holding
him account. Bad behavior. Yeah. Okay. All right. Okay. Well, we've got another one. This one is
from Travis who has a question about sin. Greetings, Paul Vathers. I have a question about sin.
What is it? And how did it come into existence?
In the past you've mentioned that sin is a spiritual being that seeks to dominate and master
people like it did cane. How did that spiritual being come into existence?
Also, in a sense, is sin a form of mistimed goodness. My understanding of creation is that
God made everything good. I've also heard Father Seraphim rose, quote,
multiple saints saying that in the Garden of Eden God eventually intends
ended, Adam and Eve, to partake of the fruit of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil.
The problem was not eating of the fruit of the tree, but eating of the tree at the wrong
time, when God told them not to.
As I have thought about this more, I have come to the conclusion that all sin on some level
could be thought of as doing the right action at the wrong time.
To commit adultery is to have sex, a good thing.
the wrong time, not with our spouse.
To commit idolatry.
is to worship. A good thing. We were made to worship, but it's done at the wrong time.
It's not directed towards God. Does this view of sin as a sort of mis-timing, a sort of lack of
chiroast timing make sense and fit into the spiritual understanding of sin outlined in the Lord of
spirits? Thank you, Father. Have a blessed rest of your day. Okay, so it's two parts, right? The first
is like where does sin as a spiritual force come from? But then also...
you know, how does that connect with this idea of?
I mean, like the second part,
we see this kind of language in some of the monastic fathers,
especially talk about passions as being,
when they become sinful, it's because they're misdirected.
Not so much like a change in time, maybe.
But I mean, a misdirection in time is a misdirection too, right?
Like, you know, I could stand outside in my backyard
and turn in circles and swing my arms around,
but if one of my children comes within arms
where each I should stop that.
Right? Because I couldn't hit them in the...
face. And I do not wish to hit them in the face. So I don't know, I mean, it's a good
question. I mean, I feel like I have some sense of both that sinfulness as a spirit, malevolent
spiritual presence comes because of demonic rebellion, right? That it's a force of actual,
an actual personal force in the world that is fallen angelic nature, right?
Right, yeah.
and so but you know the imagery that's used of sin starting with Genesis 4 is
of this demonic being but we shouldn't think that there is like this one
demonic being sin right this other one the devil or this other one right but
the idea is very much and this is not only Genesis 4 but this is how the
the details.
especially the dohending literature treats it is that, and this goes into the monastic literature,
even before the monastic literature, I was recently doing some work in the Shepard of Hermes,
and it's spelled out there, too, that this is a question of a demonic entity sort of working through you.
So, and this is what in like
first John is referred to as the works of the devil.
Yeah.
This goes all the way back.
So, demonic entities aren't able to produce things
in the world independently.
Right, so sin is when one of these spirits
sort of sees as control of a person
and that person brings those works into existence
in the world.
Yeah, now it's not necessarily...
like he used the phrase C's as control, but it's not necessarily like true possession
in the sense of like you can't help it or whatever.
Although, that does exist, right?
But is, you know, I've voluntarily I'm participating in the works of a demon and so
therefore the demon works through me.
I become his agent.
Yeah, well let me freak everybody out a little more.
All right.
In that there's more of a continuum between sinning and demonic possession than them being
two different things.
Because if you think about sin and you think about sin in the way the fathers talk about
it is the passions.
They're called passions because they make you passive.
They control you.
Rage takes control of you.
and leaves you passive, right?
Or if you think about it in terms of it.
addiction, right, as an analogy, right?
There's a point in, say, alcoholism, where you're not consciously choosing to take the
next drink anymore.
Yeah, no, it just becomes automatic.
Yeah.
And so there's not so much a line between like one of the demon possessed people we see
in the Gospels and me, quote, unquote, committing a sin, as there is sort of this range of
continue on. But that's sort of where the road leads if you continue on it. Yeah. So a difference
of with without without repentance. A difference of magnitude more than of type. Right. And so anytime
we yield to the passions, we're yielding control of ourselves and our lives to to a essentially
a demonic being, a spirit of evil, right? Is...
is what we're manifesting in what we're,
and so that produces these works, right,
which are themselves dangerous and destructive.
Yeah.
Right, in the world.
And which Christ came to destroy,
according to First John,
and the reverse is also true.
This is how the fruits of the Spirit work.
Right, when we're following Christ
and we're keeping His commandments and doing good,
we're manifesting the Holy Spirit God Himself
or participating with God Himself.
Yeah, and you become gradually more,
it doesn't become auto-
exactly, but it becomes a kind of second nature to...
Right, because our nature has changed.
Yeah.
Our nature has transformed.
Right.
Yeah.
The thing I would say about this question of...
Is sin just sort of goodness mistimed?
I see where Travis is going with that.
And I think that there's some truth to that.
But I think that the problem with that image
is that
that it sounds like when someone conceives of how they perform an action, right?
They think about their motives, they think about the process of beginning it and so on and
so forth.
But if it's, I'm just doing this at the wrong time, then that suggests that all that kind
of led up to that action is the same.
It's just, oh, whoops, it's at the wrong moment, you know?
But the truth is that the kind of movement...
movement of sin is a different movement, right, than the movement of holiness.
Even if the action itself taken as a separate, isolated sort of datum may not be evil, right?
It's not an evil thing to eat a steak, right?
But then the whole motivation that goes into putting that meat in front of an idol and
praying to that God and having the desire and intention to share a meal with that God.
That whole action is idolatry. It's not just the eating. Right. So it's not it's not just kind of mistimed
It's an an inappropriateness in a lot of ways
you know
So so I I guess I think it's it's an okay image
But I think it could be a lot fuller, you know that that's my sort of take on that. What do you think about that?
Yeah, well yeah, and you have to take into account the distinction that the fathers make between
there are blameworthy...
and there are blameless passions.
Yeah, sure.
Right? So as humans, right?
Like, we get tired, right?
We don't voluntarily get tired.
Right?
We get tired.
We get hungry, you know, we, we, you
would have the drive to reproduce,
none of which are blameworthy in and of themselves.
Right.
Right?
It's when they're indulged to excess, right?
And in the wrong way.
Right?
So there is, there is, there is,
something there in that distinction. But there are also just blameworthy passions.
Like pride is never a good thing. Greed is never a good thing. Sorry Gordon Gecko.
Yeah, those ones, yeah, the idea of mistiming them. I'll be proud at this moment, and that's okay,
but not, or I'll be greedy at this moment, but that's okay. So yeah, it doesn't quite work.
It's okay for me to be a little sloppful in butter.
right? You know, no matter how much any of us might feel that way, it's still
that's true. Yeah, yeah. Or it may reflect our actual lives. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so there's
I mean, there's a whole nest of issues here. We can maybe we'll do a show
sometime on morality and ethics of that. Like, does someone's intentions even matter?
Hmm.
Right.
When we talk about voluntary then voluntary sins.
Yeah.
Yeah, and that kind of thing, but that's for another time.
Yes indeed.
All right.
Okay, so we've got one from, he didn't say his name, but it's Socrates or Socrates, I
guess if you're going to so great.
So great.
Yes.
That's a call back to a lovely film from the 1980s.
All right.
This is one from Socrates and he has a question about nakedness.
He's always asking questions.
He never giving any answers.
Right.
Right?
Here it is.
Hi, Father Andrew and Father Stephen. Thank you for the show. My understanding is that Adam
and Eve had bodies and then when they sinned they now have flesh which is what we all have.
So my question is at the end of Genesis chapter 2 it says that they were naked and were
not ashamed. So how are we to understand their nakedness in regards to the body they had
before the fall.
And also sometimes an icon
pornography, we see them getting kicked out of paradise and they have these fur
garments of skins or clothes
look like made from animals rather than the human flesh we have now. So I was wondering how to kind of reconcile the information
there. Thank you
Yeah, so this turns on this question of the garments of skin. What does it mean to be naked before you have the garments of skin and
What's the deal with iconography that shows them literally wearing animal skins?
and
I think the second part is the easiest one to me.
Just because you shouldn't take everything you've seen an icon literally.
I think it would be the way that I would put that.
Well, how would you depict that?
Like how would you depict them before the expulsion from paradise?
Yeah.
If you were going to depict them as normal humans after.
Right.
Or, you know, yeah.
Yeah, or like, or another example is
Christ in his post-resurrectional appearances, we all recognize him when we look at an icon
we see him and say, oh there's Jesus Christ. And yet, I think no one who saw him after his
resurrection immediately recognized him. Yeah, there's a lot of, well we talked about that
in that one episode. But yeah, there's a lot of weird, like, you know, no one there to ask him who he
was because they do it with Christ. Like, that's kind of a weird circumlocution. Suggested that
That's what-
There's a question that arose in their minds.
Who is this weight?
No, this has to be him.
Yeah.
So that's kind of an odd thing.
Right.
So, like I said, you can't take it.
I don't think you can just simply take it literally.
And again, this is a patristic image, the idea that the garments of skin represent a change
in human nature.
Right.
And aren't just, here's some leather guys.
but that's an iconographic way of conveying.
that right right and I have difficulty thinking of another one let alone a better one to convey that
and clearly clearly actual iconographers have had difficulty and and depicted as well people far
more talented and blessed than I ever so yeah so what does it mean for them to be naked and unashamed
yeah so the the garments of skin aren't an answer to the problem of them being naked
mm
already remember gotten like leaves to try to solve that problem. Once they realized
they were naked. Right? There's all exchange who told you they're naked. So the issue
of them being naked in unashamed is that they're naked and don't realize that they're naked.
Yeah. And then after the knowledge of good and evil, they realize that they're naked. Right?
So what is the nakedness doing in this? This is basically trying to convey to us the idea
that there.
innocent. Right. Remember the knowledge of good and evil throughout the Old Testament every
time it's referred to later refers to maturity. Yeah. Right.
toward being an adult. Right. And so this is them trying to circumvent, right, growing in the
grace of God and the knowledge of God and trying to seize maturity, right, for themselves.
Yeah. Well, I mean, it's post-haste and it's notable that when, you know, when the Lord encounters
them at
their transgression, they said, you know, we hid because we were naked. He said, you know,
as you said, who told you were naked? And then immediately, wait, did you eat of the tree
that I told you not to eat from? So it's connected. It's directly connected, that their knowledge of
their nakedness comes as a result of this transgression. Right. And so think about, and this was true in
in the Inc. World 2, little kids run around naked all the time.
Oh yes.
Often prefer it.
Yes.
Put your clothes back on, please.
Little girls run around topless, right?
Like, nobody thinks anything of it,
and they don't think anything of it.
Right.
It's only later on as they mature and come to know those
more that they develop a sense of shame and want to cover up.
Right?
Yeah.
And that becomes appropriate.
So that's what the story is trying to tell us.
Right, you know, it's that...
This is their innocent, right?
They're sort of childlike beforehand.
Yeah.
All right.
Right?
And so yeah.
Yeah.
OK.
Well, we've got one more before we take our first break.
This is from Nathan.
Hi.
My name is Nathan.
I'm from Dallas, Texas.
And my question is about the most recent blessing
episode and how blessing relates to justice in wisdom.
Because it seems to me that blessing and justice
are practically synonymous.
since God founded creation.
on his wisdom and his wisdom undergirds all of reality. If you're a wise man, then you live by that
wisdom that God used by which God wishes us to live, whereas justice is being set in proper order
relative to creation, both in your interior man and in the external relations. So that's again
proper ordering in relation to creation and God like wisdom is. And then
blessing is that state of
being properly ordered in relation to creation. So I don't really understand
is the wise man equivalent to the just man and equivalent to the blessed man.
I'm not really understanding any sort of distinction between those three terms.
So as far as any sort of practical life is laid out. So if you could clarify that, I would greatly
appreciate it. Thanks very much and God bless. Alright I mean I think it's a good question.
My initial take on that is that it's to say that, yes, these are all pointing ultimately at the same thing,
but kind of pointing from different angles.
Right? Like wisdom is about the knowledge of doing the right thing.
Right? Often gained through experience.
And justice is how things are supposed to be. Right?
And then blessing is a way of talking about establishing justice, especially with regards to oneself.
you know that
that it's about putting yourself in that just state.
But I don't know, I mean, is he,
I don't think they're exactly synonymous
in the sense that they're just all,
mean exactly the same thing.
But I think he's right that they all kind of point
in the same direction, but maybe from different,
different, at least conceptual angles.
What do you think of that?
Right.
Yeah, sort of, yeah, they're all related, right?
So justice, properly speaking, right,
is the order in creation.
Right. The actual order where everything is in its place and everything is. Right.
And so that's directly related to blessedness, right, because at the end of the creation
days, right, God blesses the things He created. Right. That's there in the text.
So blessedness is the state of part of the creation.
with the whole. So just to man and the blessed man is the same
met person. Yeah, I just wanted to clarify like you said that God blesses
everything after he made it. This is when he says, this is when it says
and God called it good. Is that what you're talking about?
That's that's also he yeah, yeah, but he also on humans
and, uh, it produces a, uh, plastic.
Okay.
Um, and, um, so.
So the blessed man is the man who is, that also makes him a just man, right?
But again, it's two different perspectives.
The just is everything is set in order, right?
The person is set in order.
Blessed is the sort of, I guess, phenomenological side, the experience of that, right?
That state of blessedness that's reflected by, right?
And then wisdom has to do with the perception and understanding of that work.
That's in creation and that's in human life.
And so this is why in the wisdom literature and the Old Testament, like you read Proverbs
and there's all this stuff about ants, right?
Like different elements of creation and then drawing connections from that order to the
ordering of human life, right?
So wisdom is the ability to proceed.
leave that order, what is just and what is right, right?
And that's why when we get, for example,
oh, we're gonna show how wise Solomon is,
we have him judging a court case.
Because he's able to perceive the truth
of how things are rightly ordered.
And because of that, he's able to resolve
these injustices and correct them
because he's aware of
aware of that order and it's and the fool is the person who doesn't then understand how these things work. Yeah, right?
Exactly. I mean to be a fool is opposite of being the wise man. Right. And so this is what's going on with the fool says in his heart
There is no God right there weren't any atheists. Yeah, right. That's that's not what this was about right. There is no God meant there's no
Consequences for what I do I can live how I want and there will be no consequence. Yeah, especially what yeah, yeah, yeah, that's not how things work
Yeah, especially when you understand this basic notion of God as as ruler, as God, the
one who establishes justice, you know, when he says there is no God, it's more like saying,
you know, no one is watching me. There's no, there's no one in charge here. You know,
it's not just, yeah, I don't believe that he God exists. It's like you said, they sing, I
can do whatever I want. You know, right. Those consequences will find him out anyway,
Right, right.
but he's a fool because he doesn't understand
and he doesn't see them coming
and he doesn't act accordingly.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
All right, well, that is the first half
of this pre-recorded episode of Laura Spirits.
We're gonna take a little break and be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat five five eight.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity that you can't trust strangers in internet
forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place to send your interested friends?
You need help finding and working.
Orthodox Church near you. My name is Father Paul Hodge. I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox
Christian Archdiocese of North America. My name is Father Joseph Lucas. I serve in the Orthodox
Church in America. My name is Father Anthony Cook. I serve in the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese
of America. And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick, Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith
Ministries and a priest of the Antiochian Archdiocese. And we're the Orthodox intro team.
If you're looking for a first stop online.
to get an introduction to the Orthodox faith.
A place to get answers to questions from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy.
A place to send your friends and not just toss them into the chaos of the internet.
A place to get help finding an Orthodox parish and get plugged into an actual Orthodox community.
Then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
Orthroxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox on ramps.
Christian life. Again, that's Orthodoxintro.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everybody. Like I said we're not actually taking calls tonight
despite what you just heard the voice of Steve say. But we are taking your
questions. We've received a lot of pre-recorded questions and so we're just kind
of running through them shotgun style and giving responses to them so father
you're ready for the second half? Yes. Alright. Okay so for our next question we
We have Father VJ.
Hi, Father Andrew and Father Stephen.
This is Father Vijay.
I'm a priest in the Indian Orthodox Church
serving in New Jersey.
Thank you so much for your podcast.
And very much love it.
Prior to listening to your podcast,
I would look at paganism and Hinduism
as nothing to be concerned with.
That there's nothing behind it.
And yet after listening to your podcast,
then I realize that we should be concerned.
We should be worried and we should be careful.
then going to your Blessings and Cursions episode.
It felt as if you were very dismissive of the curses and that there shouldn't be any concern.
And so I wanted to clarify, and actually a good sound bite, to give to the Orthodox tradition that is, you know, concerned with these curses.
And we don't in our jurisdiction Indian in just so we don't have
The the the the evil eye we have
the black tongue and we have something called Ravikalam which is like the hours of the day
that if you start something new it will be cursed.
And so, you know, I think all of our communities have, all of our jurisdictions have this concept
of our faithful are going towards us but if you can just speak to it directly and say,
How is the Orthodox Christian to handle these curses?
And in what way they should...
be careful and not.
That's really interesting to me.
I mean, number one, I'm kind of surprised actually that apparently did not have the
evil eye tradition there in India.
Whereas it's like, I mean, it's all over the everywhere.
Yeah, yeah, it's everywhere.
So I'm going to have to look into that.
But they've got the black tongue, which I've never heard of that.
It sounds like a tribe of orcs.
Right?
The black.
Black is great to play.
Right. Yeah, I kind of love it. Yeah, so I mean he's referencing the blessing in
cursus episode where we talked about those things. And I think that the thing that was
said about cursing was, if you are a baptized Christian, you know, living a
faithful life, then you kind of don't have to really worry about that. Like it's
not something that can take over.
Yet nonetheless, like if I...
For instance, some of the the the Ephchologia the book of needs
the priest you know prayer book whatever it gets translated as that you have they have a like a prayer against the evil eye
right so
I mean is it a thing or not a thing or is it something is it a thing that we don't need to worry be worried about but even though
It really is a thing or you know
I was interested that at the beginning he said you know I used to think that this is you know
We didn't have to worry about paganism, whatever, whatever, but...
But after listening to your show, I realize there actually is something there.
Actually our spirit.
Now I am deeply concerned.
Yeah, right, exactly.
And so he's from the Indian tradition where their community has the presence of Hinduism,
especially if you're in India, but I'm sure that here in the US, Indian Christians probably
know a bunch of Hindus as well.
So I mean, that's a live thing for their lives.
So I don't know, I mean, is it nothing?
Is it nothing but...
Nothing to be worried about. I mean, what's going on with this?
Yeah, so I've been, like I said, I've been fiddling around in the shepherd of Hermus,
so you're going to get some more shepherd of Hermus. All right.
That there's a same thing that one of the things that the angel tells Hermus is that
that you shouldn't be afraid of the devil
because he's powerless.
Right, because he's powerless. He's been, he's been made powerless by Christ, but you
should be afraid of the works of the devil. And the works of the devil here is not, as
we kind of mentioned in the first half, not stuff the devil might cause somebody else
to do to you. Right. It's stuff that you would do. Yeah. Right. Because when we yield to
sin, we thereby give the devil.
influence in our lives, right? And so this is why I think the church has always pushed back
against. So the temptation with the evil eye or I would presume the black tone or any of
these things is that there is also some kind of folk means by which to ward them off.
Yeah, right. Right. The little blue. So like we talked a little blue beat or the little
I amulate or...
Right. Yeah. Yeah. And like we talked about that uberitic death curse, the, you know,
putting the evil eye on someone is immediately followed by doing another incantation to protect
yourself from the evil eye, case it rebounds, and the other guy throws a baggy. Right. Right.
And so if we enter into sort of that world and that way of doing things, right,
then we're giving those things purchase in our lives.
Right?
So my presumption would be the purpose for composing a prayer. Remember prayers
aren't to like change God and they're not magic in cantations. Right. Prayers are
to change us. So writing a prayer against the evil eye would I would think be a
pastoral thing to give the concerned person something better to do than
entering into folk magic or whatever themselves. Yeah. Right. But say here pray
this prayer right?
The sprayer will remind you that Christ protects you from the demonic powers, Christ protects you from these things.
Yeah.
It takes solace in Christ through prayer rather than whatever technique is suggested by the world.
And there's kind of a whole matrix of, you know, exorcism bound up with the priesthood as well.
You know, so I think, especially like some of the prayers against the evil eye that I've seen are largely to be said by priests.
but I think there may be lay ones as well.
And of course there's lots of prayers that talk about protecting us from the attacks
of the devil and of demons, right?
Right.
I guess the idea that people have with this is that someone could through their own malevolence
or whatever do a thing that can then make bad things happen to somebody else through
Sorceress means, you know, whether it's the Valai or the Black Tung, I have to...
imagine that anti-black-tongue folk magic has got to be like amulet shaped like a black
tongue, right? I mean, that only kind of... I don't know. Father Vijay, I have to know more
about this. I really have to do this now to write and tell us. But yeah, I mean, there's
the truth is we're always under assault on one level or another by demonic forces, right?
They're always trying to drag us into their garbage. But I don't... I think this idea that
that one person can.
sort of shoot a sort of demonic magic missile, you know, that's somebody else.
I don't know. I mean, is that a thing? I mean, what do you think? Well,
it's not that different from the physical, right? Sure. Like, someone can come and punch me in the face
or, you know, stab me or burn my house down, right? Like, so I can become so terrified
that. Then I become sort of violent and militant and paranoid myself. Or I can trust God and I can
follow Christ. The same thing is true spiritually. Hypothetically, both people who are essentially
worshipping demons. Yeah, the eye.
that one person could sick a demon on another person, okay?
Right.
You know, but in the same way, do you respond to that reality
by becoming paranoid and suspicious and superstitious?
Right, and thereby destroy yourself,
or do you follow Christ,
trusting God to protect you from that,
just like all the other kinds of harm that we face every day?
Right, which I mean,
you know, as you were saying that, especially I thought,
Wow, that's so applicable.
to a lot of things in our lives right now,
with a massive spread of various kinds of theories
about bad people wanting to do bad things.
I mean, when someone presents me with one of those theories,
whether it's true or not,
I mean, there are actual conspiracies in the world, right?
And people get together and decide,
and plan to do bad things together.
Right, exactly.
Exactly, that is a thing.
So, maybe a given conspiracy theory is true or not true.
But even if they're all this is what I-
I always say to people, even if they're all true, even if the things that are being described in these are actually all true.
Our task as Christians in the world is still the same as it was before.
It's still be faithful in the midst of this.
It's still trust God for his protection.
That's still what's going on.
And sometimes I think there's an attraction to the idea of having achieved some kind of
knowledge about what's going on.
going on in the world. And that becomes a kind of addiction to itself, you know, when you
see evil everywhere constantly, right? I mean, it's not that evil isn't everywhere, but
when that's what you're focusing on, when that's what your whole life is about, then like
you said, it's this sort of addictive anxiety and failure to trust in God, really. You know,
become very nasty often in response to feel.
like they're surrounded by hostile powers. You know, if that's if that's their whole deal, right?
The emphasis and the the turning of the attention towards what is evil rather than the focusing on
what is good and being faithful in the midst of a difficult world. So yeah, fun stuff. Okay, all
Alright, well this next one comes from Kinsey.
but my friends, Pomekin Z, I'm recording from Colorado Springs, Colorado, and I am a Bible college student
with kind of a difficult question but I sense not only strength and intelligence in YouTube but also great kindness.
So you know this is kind of tender and a tricky issue. I have confidence in you guys.
I grew up Wesleyan Armenian and for a long time my family also attended various Baptist denominations.
and boom.
Both of those traditions have radically different teaching on women and their role in the church.
Now I personally have a huge heart for the ministry.
My great-grandpa, who I'm named after, was a preacher.
My dad is a pastor.
And I remember I had a passion for the ministry from a young age and I was sitting across my
at the time, beloved, Baptist head pastor.
over a meal he looked at me and said if I were to pursue those goals.
I would be a Jezebel. The Jezebel spirit, you know, is so huge in the Baptist Church.
And what I want to know is, what is the Orthodox perspective? Is there room for someone like me who is a passionate poet,
thinker, writer, artist, and minister at the Orthodox table? Is there room for me there?
And yeah, I guess that's it. Thank you guys so much for the show and everything you do.
Alright, it's a good question.
You know my, my initial response.
The first person actually started thinking about when she, especially at the end,
she was kind of describing herself.
I started thinking about Saint Cassiani,
who a number of those adjectives could be used to describe her, right?
You know, the thing that she's most remembered for, of course, in the history of the church
is as a himnographer.
And in fact, probably the greatest piece of Byzantine music
music was in the whole tradition of Byzantine
hand was written by her.
And it's the famous hymn of Cassini that's sung on Holy Tuesday
evening during Holy Week.
It's so beloved that actually in many cases,
if you look at the Holy Week schedules for a lot of churches,
it'll say Sunday night, bridegroom or throes,
Monday night, bridegroom or throes, Tuesday night,
hymn of Cassini, even though it's bridegroom or throes,
but including that hymn.
But that's such a feature that becomes the thing
that people are going there.
for. But that's not the only thing she ever wrote. She wrote lots of hymns, actually.
And they are even in translation. They are stunning pieces of work. Like this is real
theological poetry. It's really delightful and profound and moving. I mean, there's
There's a reason why the hem of Castini is so popular and it's not just because
of the kinds of musical settings that are attached to it, right?
It's because of just the great, great depth
of what's being expressed in that.
And certainly there are other examples of that
within the life of the church both historically
and of course in our own time.
And especially considering this old saying
of the one who praise truly is the truth, theologian.
You know, we tend to think of theologians as people who write books.
You know, people like you father Steven or like me got help me, but I wouldn't describe myself as a theologian
You know that that's what a theologian is or a professor or something like that, but you know
There's a great truth to this saying that that theology is really about prayer and if that's really true
That the the person who is really advanced in prayer is the sort of the real theologian on some level then
The number one example of that is the Lord's mother
there. You know the highest.
of all the saints is a woman,
that the ministry that she gave,
not just to us, although that's really important,
but to the Lord is above all other possible ministries.
Like you can't achieve something greater
as a human being than what she did, right?
And that's not a cop-out response.
I recall, I can't remember which episode it was,
but we were having a conversation about,
I think it was in response to a caller who called in and had a similar question about this.
If you remember, Father, you know, that, and you gave a great answer about mothering
and how motherhood is not, is, of course, the number one way people think about it and
I should think about it is about, you know, bearing children and taking care of them,
but that there's mothering that all women engage in whether they have children in the flesh
or not, right? That's the, what?
women are in their telos is motherhood, and this is built into the creation from the beginning.
And I think our modern world tends to denigrate that so much that it's like, well, that's
second prize or whatever.
But it's really not.
And I think that the Christian tradition, especially in the person of the mother of God, emphasizes
how much it's really not.
again this is the highest possible place that a human...
a human being can have is the one that she has, more honorable than the chair of him, you know,
and so forth.
But I mean, I would simply say, Kenzie, that, I mean, it's true, right?
You didn't ask about this, but it's true that the Orthodox Church does not ordain women
as priests, you know, as clergy.
And for, I think for a good take on that, Father Stephen wrote a great blog article on his
block the whole council of God. Block.
called priesthood and masculinity.
And it's a really good piece
and it talks about how priesthood is integral to masculinity,
not just for ordained men, but just for men in general.
Right?
So it's true, yes, we don't ordain women as clergy,
but I think that a huge part of the problem that we have
is that we've identified clergy with power
and we've identified power as the highest thing
that people should have.
And so therefore, if you don't give it to some people,
it's because you're trying to keep the...
down. Now, you didn't say that, Kenzie, and I appreciate that. But I thought I would
just kind of put that out there. But I would say that, you know, based on the things that
you say that you love and the talents and skills that you have, I mean, all of that can
be put in service to Christ. There absolutely is a place for you at the table of the Lord
and the Orthodox Church. I mean, every person is integral to the body of Christ. It doesn't
matter whether they're a hand or a foot or a spleen or whatever. We're all needed and
We're all recording.
It's quite weird, really.
So that's some of the thoughts that I would have about that.
I guess the other thing I would add is simply,
is that I could not live as an orthodox Christian
without the ministry that women within the church do,
not just sort of in support of the parish, whatever,
but in my own personal life as well.
So I mean, absolutely critical,
absolutely irreplaceable, right?
So Father Stephen, I don't know,
do you have anything you wanted to add to that or whatever?
I just add, I mean...
There is a lively tradition of female monasticism that often gets left out of these conversations.
Right?
There are spiritual mothers.
There are abuses and a lot of the activities they do.
Our understanding of ordination is less about activity.
This is a comparison based on the background that the caller said she was from.
They tend to define ministry in terms of certain activities.
So.
like standing in front of the church and giving a homily, right? They would say,
that's ministry, that's reserved to these people, right? But,
absences of convinced, for example, frequently give homilies.
Oh, sir.
To the female monastics there. There are female monastics who are blessed
to hear confessions. They don't give the
absolutely it again, but
They hear the confession and they give advice and then the person goes back to their usually
parish priest and just receives the absolution.
That's a good example, right?
Because the activity there, most of the activity, other than reading the prayers at the end,
most of the activity there is being done by the female monastic.
But the role of delivering absolution is reserved to that priest.
not to men to presbyters.
Yeah, right.
Right.
And bishops, because bishops are still presbyters.
But deacons can't do it.
Laymen can't do it, right?
So that is a role that is reserved to specific people who are chosen from among the men
of the church.
And not even all presbyters.
Not even all presbyters are given a blessing to hear, to give absolution to your
Right, right.
And, and, and, and lay mail.
monastics camp. Right. Right. So, yeah, so it's based on this particular role. Right.
But the overarching thing, and this is a thing that's not directed in the color in particular,
this is directed at everyone. First and foremost, me is that all of us, when we approach serving
the church, have to wrestle a little bit with our ego. Right? Because...
The reality is if we're serving if that word means anything, right?
That I'm here to serve the church that that means I'm going to do whatever the church needs me to do
Yeah, it doesn't mean I'm gonna do what I want to do
Yes, sir servants don't show up to the master and say so this is what I'm going to be doing
Yeah, the servant goes to the man and the master's Christ, you know, they go to the master and says what do you want me to do?
So if the church tells me that what it needs me to do is scrub toilets, then I need to go and scrub toilets.
Even if I'm an arch-priest with a Ph.D.
If what my parish needs me to do is go clean the toilets, then that's what I need to go to.
Right. And so we can't ever approach the church with, um, I, uh, this is,
I'm confident these are my gifts. This is what I'm going this is what I want to do and
Will this church let me do it? Well, if not then I'll find some place that will that's very dangerous
Yeah, and I don't I don't get the sense that Kenzie was saying that but there are
No, that's what I said. It's not you do that. Yeah, it's not directed at her men and women men and women
I've known men that I've had men approach me and say you know, I'm
especially this is actually fairly common. I'm more dainty than this.
and I want to join the Orthodox Church,
but I want to make sure that I can be clergy.
I'm like, you need to give up on that.
If you want to be Orthodox, be Orthodox,
but you can't just say,
look, I'm coming here because I'm going to be clergy.
I'm like, ah, yeah.
And there have certainly been people
of the Orthodox Church men who wanted to be
or date to some office and couldn't get it.
And so have left and gone somewhere else where they could.
So this is not directed at her or even at just women.
And just all of us have this tendency we have to fight.
Yep.
With our ego.
So we have to all-
keep in mind that all of this is service and that means we do whatever Christ and His church need
us to do at any given point in time, whether it's something we really love doing or something that
like quitting toilets or walking around after liturgy on Sunday throwing away used coffee cups
that people left laying everywhere. But now I'm going on a personal rant. Yeah, not. Right? But
That's it. Right. You know. Yeah.
That's part of the reality of being in ordained ministry is you do a whole lot of stuff other than you know,
Litergize indeed, but not all is fun and enjoyable. Yeah like paperwork. Yep
Not me man. I got out of that
Yeah, you'd never have to do paperwork at all ever. Yeah, ever
Okay, all right well
Thank you very much for that question Kenzie. It was there was
Thank you, thank you.
All right, this next one comes.
from Lane who has a question about atonement.
Hi, this is Lane in O'Cala, Florida, and I had a question about the word aton.
So in the atonement episode, you guys said that to atonement just meant to cover.
So that got me wondering, not only how did something so simple get so theologically complicated,
but more so, there are lots of places in the Bible where things are covered, like Noah's
covered up in his nakedness.
Um, you know, stuff is covered up all over the place, but are are those also atonement?
Are they like a different kind of covering?
What's what makes this kind of covering get its own special word and those not or maybe they do?
Uh, thanks.
I love the show.
Yeah.
Right.
So that was actually one of my favorite episodes was the atonement episode.
It's been a while since we did that now.
I feel like it was over a year maybe.
Yeah.
Um.
We talked about the day of Atoneman and how that is fulfilled in Christ ultimately.
And I think that the short answer to what Lane is asking is that this word covering is just a general word, just like it is in English.
But if you talk about covering in a particular context, then it takes on a greater meaning.
But of course the word English word atone.
was actually coined to be a translation for this word, right?
And so it becomes a translation that has a specific theological purpose within the English language.
But if you're just simply reading it in ancient Greek, then, or in Hebrew, then it's just a general term
but you see it's used in this one particular context.
I think the reason that it gets so complex in the way that Christians of various stripes
about it is that it's such a key moment in in salvation history, right? That
of course there's going to be just a huge amount of reflection on that. And when
you have big sea changes like the reformation's ideas about what salvation means,
then you are going to, you know, it's just going to become debate about it, right? And of course,
And so then that that complicates the whole the whole matter, right?
But I
It doesn't mean that the more general uses of the term no longer apply or that every time
you see the word, you know, that KFR isn't a KFR root, is that what it is?
Well, roughly.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
When you wherever you see that root, you should think, oh, this has to do with the atonement
of Christ.
You know, it may not.
It may just be the cover on your Tupperware.
Or the Ark of the Covenant?
Or the Ark of the Covenant.
Exactly, it could just be that kind of...
But also, I think a lot of the significance of course comes because of the day of atonement,
right?
It's the day of covering, the day of cleansing and cleaning up and doing all that.
So, that's kind of my hot take on that, Father.
Yeah, well, slight home actually is not actually a normal Greek word.
The Greek word seems to be kind of a coinage.
Oh, that's right.
That's right.
Yeah, this this type of covering from other
general types, right? That's particularly related to sacrificial usage. In terms of the complications,
I think we get all blame, Avril Lavigne. But that is just Canadians.
Yeah, right. So really, honestly, the reason why you get, and you don't have a similar history of
of theorization about...
the atonement in the east, you just don't. Right? You don't have people proposing atonement
theories. You don't have people arguing them against each other. It just doesn't happen
in the east. Now, some are particularly Protestant apologists like to argue that's just because
we never figured atonement out. We're just like a bunch of privitives. Like we didn't figure
out atonement, we didn't figure out so tearyology. But that's because they basically bought into
our 19th century German friends that all of these things
have evolved in the church, right? And so we're just stuck at this earlier phase, whereas
you know, German Protestantism in the 19th century is the pinnacle of all human religion, right?
But in the West, it really gets so complicated because you have a series of, as theology is being
work about you have a series of questions that get asked.
Each one is sort of in j...
to buy the expressions of previous tears of theology.
For example, this is a very rough and very quick genealogy, but for example, St. Augustine ends up kind of smushing together,
becoming of death upon humanity and sin and guilt. He kind of webbed as those together.
Right. And so as the last being...
unable to read Greek post St. Augustine,
are reading mainly St. Augustine.
That gets carried on.
Well, that starts raising questions, right?
Because in the East, for example,
we have a separation between death and sin, right?
It's these two different things.
We could say that, for example,
Christ's resurrection redeems everyone from death,
but it does not redeem everyone from sin, right?
Those are dealt with separately.
Whereas in the West, if those start to get smudged together, you get, well, wait a minute.
So then why doesn't Christ sacrifice redeem everyone from sin?
And so you get Peter Lombard comes along and makes this sufficiency, efficiency distinction,
right?
Where he says, well, Christ sacrifices sufficient to save everyone.
But it is only efficient.
only actually saves the people who do XYZ, right?
And that basic distinction ends up being the basis for basically the Protestant Reformation.
Yeah.
Is the argument over, well then, what is the XYZ?
How does it now and when does it get applied?
And then things move on from there, right?
So, if you say, well, it's sufficient, it's only efficient for these people.
What's the sort of mode or mean?
of transfer. So you get the idea of merit, you get the idea of, and that gets broken down
further. So it all becomes more elaborate because people are asking questions, but the
questions they're asking, we're really engendered by the solutions to the previous problem.
Right. Right. And so in the east where we didn't face those same problems, we didn't
come up with answers because we didn't face the questions. And so then those didn't raise
the further questions.
And so you have this whole thing in the West thing.
Yeah, it's built up on a, frankly, on a foundation that we don't share.
So yeah, right, right.
It's like saying, you know, why don't you have the answer to this English language riddle that was written 50 years ago?
Like, well, because we're not speaking English, you know, you know, as a sort of analogy to that. So yeah.
Right.
So if someone comes to an orthodox person who understands orthodox theology and says,
are the merits...
of Christ's sufferings imputed or infused into a human being, right? We don't have an answer
to that question, right, because we don't have all the pre-existing superstructure, right?
That leads to that question. Yeah, yeah, exactly, exactly. Okay, well, this next one is from
the same Travis that we heard from earlier. Greetings, podfathers. So my questions have to do with
theosis.
and demonosis. My understanding is that everything we say and do either draws us closer to God or
draws us closer to the demons. What I'm left wondering is, can what other people say and do lead to
theosis and demonosis of others? For example, if a priest blesses me, is he an instrument of theosis
in me. By the same token, can act performed to someone lead them to demonosis.
a part from them consciously sinning.
Also, on the far ends of theosis and demonosis, are there certain things that need to happen
for one to become a saint or a demoniac?
Clearly becoming a saint requires outpourings of grace from God in a unique way.
Has someone that becomes a demoniac undergone a similar process in the opposite direction?
their particular sins we should avoid.
if we do not want to become a demoniac.
And what are some of the things we can do
if we really want to become a saint?
Former darts, Travis.
So my response to the second part is
that my understanding of both sanctity and demonization
is that the difference between like what a saint is
and what, you know, the very good man in my
parish, or even the pretty good man or woman in my parish, whatever, is really not so much
a difference of kind as of degree.
That there's not, I wouldn't necessarily say that there's a unique outpouring of grace
that turns someone into a saint whereas they weren't before.
Right?
Now certainly there are some people who are canonized, which is to say that there was
a process that the church went through to recognize someone as a saint and to public
invent right then in an organized way, but that's not what makes someone a saint. There are plenty of
people who truly are holy people actually saints that don't have any church services written for them
and maybe we don't even know their names or that they ever existed you know for whatever reason.
So I don't think that there's like a line that you can cross and like oh now I've made it now I'm
a seat, right?
So I mean my response to this question is there a thing that you can do truly to be
become a saint or a thing you should, some sin you should really avoid to become a demoniac.
I mean, it's, it's really just a matter of that, that faithfulness to Christ. It's not like,
oh, well, if I, if I engage in this one kind of faithfulness, then that's kind of the
shortcut to sanctity. I don't think there's any shortcuts to that. There are some, I wouldn't
say it's like, it's magic to be, to become deeply sinful, but certainly there are some
extreme sins you can engage in that do radically disfigure the human person. Right.
Bye.
You know, not all sins, all sins are bad, but some sins are worse.
You know, like having suddenly an envious thought and accepting and entertaining it for a few
minutes is definitely not as bad as going and murdering someone, right? These are not the same
degree of evil. Both are demonizing, both can push someone further in direction of evil.
but they're not the same thing.
So yeah, I mean, there might be shortcuts to hell
on some level, but it's not like
if you do this one thing versus this,
then that'll definitely take you.
I mean, someone could become a very dark person,
but have never done anything like illegal
or some extreme act, you know?
So I don't know, that's my take on that part of it.
Yeah, I don't know.
And the first part, I don't know.
I mean, whether you can, yes, I do believe
that the things that we do can affect other people,
but I wouldn't say that they do it apart from their,
especially if it's someone as a baptized Christian,
apart from their participation in it, right?
But I don't know, especially when you're talking about
the world of outside of Christ.
Then...
that's probably a different ball game. I don't know. Father, Father, what do you
have to say all that? Well, I mean, a lot of the way people think about
canonization now is this weird nominalism where, yeah, like somehow,
to be something you have to be recognized as that or being recognized as
something being validated by someone else as something is what makes you that
Yeah right
So, I mean, if someone sees me and recognizes me as a priest, that doesn't make me a priest,
right? I was already a priest. But in our modern world, we have this non-lost thing where,
well, no, if no one else recognizes it, then I'm not really that thing. That's like the cause of
some kind of suffering, right? And I need to be validated, right? So, yeah, we recognize Saints.
they're already saints. Before we record like you have the church never record.
They're still saints.
So yeah, it's a question of, again, more of a spectrum of other people affecting things.
Obviously in both cases, we're talking about cooperation.
So if I'm cooperating with demons in rebellion and you come and cooperate with me,
join me in my sin as I'm joining them in their rebellion.
I mean, I guess that I would be the mediator of demonization to you.
This is why being an archeric or cult leader would be a very bad thing to be.
And this is talked about in scripture, temptations about to come but woe to him through whom
they come.
that it is more serious to lead others into our sin
than justice in ourselves, right?
And then vice versa, right?
If someone is cooperating with the grace of God,
then and you cooperate with that, right?
So if you're a priest is cooperating with God
working in your life, right?
By speaking to you preaching to you,
teaching you something, advising you in confession, right?
And you cooperate with that.
And confession might be a good example, right?
He says to you, here are some things you can do
to help you.
in this struggle, you can now cooperate with that.
You can now do follow through and do those things,
and continue to struggle, in which case,
then yeah, that priest will sort of,
and that act and confession will become,
it's a grace for you,
or you can reject it or ignore it or rebel against it.
Yeah.
Right?
But the key factor there is still your own cooperation.
Yeah, I mean, he gave the example of a priest
giving a blessing.
I mean, to receive the blessing,
you have to receive.
the blessing. Yeah, Father bless. You know, like, you know, I mean, I, it's, it's
something I think about sometimes like, for instance, if I drive by the house of
somebody I know, that I may, you know, as a priest, I may give a blessing in the
direction of their home. That's not a magical act. It's a prayer for them. And
God may well send them good thoughts or something helpful for them that day in
response to that prayer, but it's not like that I just put a magical word on their
house.
or on them or whatever, they still have to cooperate with it.
It doesn't make them holier because I'd give them a drive-by blessing.
Right.
So.
All right.
Well.
Yeah.
Do you do that a lot?
I buy it spray blessings in neighborhoods.
I mean, I, you know, where I live actually there are a number of other people who belong to
the Paris that I'll live in this in my little town.
So yes, I do give drive-by blessings.
But you don't bless the people who don't go to the Paris.
You leave them under the curse.
Apparently, I also throw blessings and ambulances with their lights on and police officers.
Regardless. Yeah, exactly. I don't know. I mean, how am I supposed to know?
It's true.
Right. Thanks for calling me out there.
No problem. It's part of my job. It's right. It is.
All right. Okay. So this next one comes from Nikolai.
Father Andrew and Father Stephen, this is Nicolai from Austin, Texas.
I can adequately describe my gratitude to you both for the great work you're doing on this podcast and your other publications.
Thank you very much.
And my question is, I'm very interested in, you mentioned a few times how spiritual and material reality are not necessarily separate.
I'm very interested to understand more about how the you got.
the union between the spiritual reality and the physical reality.
It's a concept that I can't quite grasp, not sure it's graspable in this life entirely,
but I know you two will have more to say about it.
I think if you cared at some color to it, thank you very much.
All right.
So those those were kind words and it sounded like they were uttered
from the bottom of a mind shaft.
Right.
I know.
I don't know where he was.
I hope everything turned out okay for him.
It's definitely pretty,
as in the audio world, we call it every live room,
a very live room.
I don't know, I don't know how to respond to this.
Like what connects the spiritual,
I guess my initial response would be that
we tend to think in terms of categories
of material and spiritual,
But my sense is that at least...
And the pre-modern way of thinking tends to think more in terms of scene and unseen.
You know, that there's not a physical stuff in a material, and a spiritual stuff.
There's just creation and some of its scene and some of its unseen. I don't know.
It's just a lot of stuff. Yeah, just so much stuff. All the stuff.
What's ancient Hebrew for stuff? I don't know. Is there one?
Well, Debar can mean a thing.
Debarine, I guess would be things.
You know the fun thing as it were about the English word thing is actually originally meant
a meeting.
And like we're having a thing.
Like people use it.
Yeah, that's the correct usage.
Right, right.
Exactly.
That's the ancient usage.
That's the old English usage.
So there you go.
It exists in the Norse too, Ting.
It meant the same thing.
Later it becomes about.
you know, and and
a thing as we as we put it now an object or whatever, but yeah originally
meant so. So Ben Grimm is the Everloven Blue Eye meeting. Yes, he's basically
sort of walking committee. Okay, a rocks. That kind of works exactly.
Kind of works. He's a rock committee. A rock group as it were. We haven't had
a culture banter in this episode for people to get a throw in.
Oh, yes. Okay. So connective reality.
Aim, right. Do your thing.
Anyway, that's digging in the crates.
So, yeah, so the thing is
probably intended that we have kind of a sensory processing
disorder.
What I've been by that is.
So the original meaning of the term common sense was a way to refer to the way in which our
Senses are five senses are naturally integrated to each other
Right when when we're when as a human we're functioning normally
Right, we don't have like vision and hearing and taste and smell and touch as like
disassociated stimuli
Right.
But from them we have a quote-unquote common sense that sort of constructs a world out of
all that data taken in by those various senses.
So we associate a smell with something that we see, right, or taste or feel, that is
sound with something we see.
But when it comes to the news, which is we said is a sensory organ that's aimed at the
spiritual world, probably be
because it was blind for a good chunk of our lives.
And we're, as Christians, just beginning to use it again.
At least I am, the saints, much better.
But we don't really have it integrated with the other five.
So we have the five that we're used to using
to engage with material reality.
and then maybe
we were starting to get the beginnings of some kind of very shadowy and dim spiritual perception.
But not only is it shadowy and dim because we haven't exercised it much but it's not integrated with the rest.
So when you read stories from the lives of the saints and even stories,
I mean we refer to Alishaga Azia Bunch because it's an obvious idea.
Right, you have faiths.
for whom these things are integrated.
Right, and they will just see angels and demons
and spiritual realities, right, and principalities and stuff.
And that's integrated with the material world.
It's not that sort of, they block out the material world
and go into some spiritual realm, right,
where they see these things, right?
And then they return to the material world
where the rest of us live.
It's that they're seeing the holder.
reality and they're seeing elements of that that we can't see. So it's like if we lack
one of the five senses, right? So if we were like, you know, the man born blind who's
gospel, we read not that long ago as we record this, you know, we would have no concept of
what color is. We would have no concept of, you know, what vision is or how it works, right?
We'd have our other four senses, right? And we'd understand how those work and they would
be integrated.
thing, right? But we wouldn't have, we wouldn't have that one. And so in the same way, it's sort of,
and I obviously, I'm not a saying, this is obvious to anyone who's met me or heard me talk or
knows who I am. But, you know, so I can't, it's not like I have this and I'm now trying to explain
it to you who lack it. I don't have it either. I'm reading accounts from people who do.
Yeah, ancient people and states of the church and
Reading their attempts to describe it to people who don't have it and then I'm trying to pass that on second hand to other people who like me
So
The key thing in terms of how they're related is simply that they're they're
related in the same way that
to further this analogy, the same way that smell and taste are related, the same way that
hearing and sight are related.
These are just elements of the created order that we can or can't experience.
All those colors of mantis shrimp can see.
The way those are related to the colors I can see.
It's part of creation in the same sense.
This is the really hard part to get over.
say yes they're part of creation too, but we still have, well, but kind of in a different
sense, right? Because it's higher or different or, right? But no, it's in the same sense.
And angel is a creature in the same sense that I am a creature. We're just different
types of creature. Yeah. Yes. The same sense that a badger is a creature, right? Yeah.
Different types. Yeah. This kind of distinction occurred to me a little bit this morning when
I was reading so today when we're
this, this is a secondary feast of St. Theodore the General. And so I was reading, you know,
the brief account of his life this morning. And, you know, when he was headed towards his
martyrdom, he was tortured, I mean, all kinds of horrible things were done to him, right,
disfiguring stuff. And then, and then just simply says, you know, like the next morning
or something, he was found whole. And because of this, many people believed in
Christ, right? And so they're mentioning with the authorities behead him. And it struck
me once again, like, well, what was that? What was that like when that wholeness happened?
What was it like when people saw that that's what had occurred? I'm pretty sure there
probably weren't like some explosions and sparkles and, you know, like there was nothing,
there was nothing woo, woo about it. It was just simply like, whoa, he's, hey, what do
know, peace healthy.
in every way. You know, that there was not like we expect quote unquote spiritual things
to have some kind of special effect attached to them, right? And yet you never like it
when miracles, for instance, happen in the scriptures. You know, like the healing of the
blind man, it doesn't say that, you know, suddenly everything went hazy and he opened
his eyes and woo, you know, it was just simply that he could see. Now he could see I was blind.
but now I can see. Well, there's that one instance where he could see men walking around like trees.
Right. First. Right. Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, his percent, which is a great phrase.
I see men walking around like trees walk around. Yeah. Oh, like, wait. How do you know what a tree looks like?
Yeah. That's the other question I ask. Sorry. Thanks. I mean, maybe it's what they feel like.
But you know, so obviously for him, you know, he went through a transitional experience before he
Try it, side again. But I mean, there's no indication that anyone else...
saw magical sparkles in the air or something when this happened.
You know, there was no signs of sorcery or anything like that.
Light shining from the sky.
Yeah.
Right, exactly.
It's not that those kinds of experiences never happen, like Moses' face shining or this
kind of stuff, but it does not always happen, or even often happen, such that we should
think that that's sort of the signal that there's a spiritual thing happening.
You know, it's just part of the warping weft of,
or warping woof, I can never remember if that's,
I think they're both right, of the way that life is.
And people simply receive that.
I think about, for instance, I probably mentioned this
before on the show, St. Nicholas,
the limiter of Hesah, a homily where he says,
miracles are, God gives many gifts
and miracles are just simply some of God's gifts
at which men marvel.
That's what he says.
He doesn't...
say that they have a there's a separate unique thing to them. That's why they're
wonder workers. Right. Right. Those are the workers who are wonder workers. Yeah, but yeah, it's the
most I know is going to be disappointing to a lot of people, but the most common way God
heals people is like rest and their immune system. Right. That's the action of God.
But that's what he uses most of the time.
And then next is probably medicine.
Yeah, a big part of it's a big problem is just the problem of interpretation
That we tend to interpret things in the wrong way
You know so right, but yeah, I've got this this barrier right this barrier between God's action or angels and demons and
The material right no right God heals people using their immune system right yeah right which is a good material thing
Yeah, yeah, exactly. Okay, one last question.
before we wrap up for our second break. So this is from Father Aaron. Why did Christ give
Himself to us in the form of flesh and blood such a provoking act? Was it necessary to say,
eat my flesh and drink my blood? This would especially have been a setup for the chosen people,
to do his own flesh and blood because he had established strict laws against consuming
and against consuming unclean flesh.
Psalm 105, they sacrifice their daughters,
their sons and daughters into demons,
they poured out in a sin blood.
Certainly, drinking blood would have been associated
with pagan sacrifices and gross things
and demonic things.
So was all this demonic sacrifice in the collective memory
of the Jews and was the Eucroismate to heal that.
The Jews are forbidden to drink blood, whether sacrificial victims or any other.
So why does Jesus introduce this practice, which is so likely to scandalize, and much more
akin to pagan practices than to Jewish ones?
That's a cool question.
So it's kind of the cannibalism, pagan sacrifice, eucharist thing.
How do they relate to each other?
Why does Jesus give us His blood?
to drink and his flesh to drink even after all of those commands against doing exactly
that kind of thing.
What's that all about, Father?
Well, first of all, the flesh part is relatively easier than the blood part, right?
Right.
Very easy, but these are two separate things, right?
They've been...
They've been eating flesh as part of sacrifices already, but not...
Not human flesh.
Human flesh, right?
Yeah, not again.
Right, right.
So, yeah.
And this is, right, eating is the way you participate
in a sacrifice.
Right, that's the way you take part in it.
Right.
And then sort of the human part,
I'll deal with here under the blood part.
Right, so I mean, that's the first immediate thing.
So the idea is that Christ sacrifice
is the sacrifice to end all sacrifices.
And therefore we participate in it.
Right.
Then we do that through the Eugress.
So in terms of the blood, so the commandments against blood, if you go back to where they're
first stated and where blood is first talked about blood is representing the life of a creature,
we have to remember that before the flood, there's also that was not permitted to eat meat
in general at all.
killing of animals and
And so what you have with the consumption of blood, because they weren't just prohibited
from drinking sacrificial blood, they weren't allowed to eat meat with the blood in it,
right, completely outside of sacrifices, right.
So the blood had to be drained or drinking blood in any context.
So the blood being the life of the thing, then directly consuming the life.
on life, right, was sort of symbolic man as creditor, right? We talked about this when we
talked about werewolves. Yeah, right. Right. And this is what cannibalism is associated
with, through the man becoming predatory, right? And Adam and Eve, obviously in the garden
are not predatory, right? The language that's used there is they're eating the fruit from
trees, which means they're not even killing plants.
Right? It's only after the expulsion for paradise that Adam has to bring forth food from the
ground with sweat. The fruit was the parties offering it themselves to him, right? sort
sort of cooperatively. But so the predatory nature is in sort of the opposite of that, right?
And so what we see with Christ then giving his flesh and blood to us is an inversion.
It's this exact opposite of predatory.
Right.
Christ does not say, you know, to murder him and he can't.
To murder him and cannibalize him.
Right.
But he offers himself, this is why St. John's Gospel is so clear over and over and over again that no one takes his life from him.
down. Right? And he can take it up again. So Christ offers himself to us as food. And a lot of
our prayers say that, say John of Damascus in what we sing in place of the Cherubic hymn on
Holy Saturday says that, right? The Christ is offering Himself to us. And that includes his blood,
which is his life, which is the life of God, which is immortal, which he...
offers to us to share in it. Right? So it is the inversion of that kind of predatory sacrifice
that culminates in sort of human sacrifice and cannibalism and where wolfism. Right?
Christ's self-offering is the exact inverse of that.
All right. Well, with that, we're going to go ahead and go to our second and final break and we will
be right back.
young will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
welcoming gifts sacrifice in the Bible and Christian life by Jeremy Davis.
You'll find some
surprising answers in this book. You'll learn that sacrifice had a very different significance
for ancient people than it does for us today. You'll hear how it drifted away from this ancient
significance into a fundamentally different meaning in our modern world. You'll discover how
Old Testament sacrifices were gifts from the heart only tangentially related to killing and death.
You'll see in Christ's cross the ultimate gift that ushers us.
into communion with God. And you'll find inspiration to offer your own gifts alongside
Christs, inviting God into your life.
Welcome in gifts, sacrifice in the Bible and Christian life.
Now available in paperback, eBook, and audiobook at store.inchantfaith.com
Yeah, there's that crunchy metal theme.
Thanks a lot once again for that Rob, we appreciate it.
the third half of the Lord of Spirits on this pre-recorded episode.
So it's once again, don't call in.
We're not here to talk to you today.
But we are talking to you because you sent
to New Yorkers.
You could call in and just see what happens.
You could call.
I mean, that is always an option.
But.
Who knows?
Somebody might be there.
You know, yeah.
But anyway.
So all right, well, we've got six more questions
and then we'll wrap it up for this
period recorded episode of Spirit.
So this first one comes to us
from our friend.
Emilian.
Greetings, fathers.
Later this year, God willing, I am going to marry my fiance.
So in light of the topics covered before on this podcast, could you talk a bit about the
Holy Sacrament of Marriage and specifically about what it does accomplish?
I hope this question isn't too broad.
I am sure a series of episodes on the Holy Mysteries
on the way, but I'd like to know more about this particular one at this time. Thank you for your
excellent work. I love how he says he's sure that a series is on the way.
He thinks it's like I play at things that are in advance. That's a spectacle.
So number one, Emiliano Lamontzani. Congratulations on getting married later this year.
So if I remember, I think Emilia on this is from Romania.
So yeah, great, good for you, man.
Good for you.
I mean, I think the main way to answer this question
is sit down and read the wedding service.
Like it tells you, I'm not trying to say that to be glib,
but it's a talk out.
Yeah.
Good night, everybody.
But I mean, it does say it.
It's about yoking people together
for the sake of their salvation to bring...
glory to God to bring forth children into the world, to be raised in faithfulness to Christ.
Right? And there's even some cool Theosius language having to do with the saints, like
the couple will shine like the stars of heaven. I love that line. And of course, as a lot of
people point out, there's this theme of martyrdom there as well. But as with all the sacraments
to take you from one mode of life to another.
So baptism does that.
right? Ord nations certainly does that. And I know a lot of people wouldn't consider
tonsure to monasticism as a sacrament, although I think that some of the fathers do call it
that a holy mystery. I mean, we're not bound to the number seven. I don't think.
Yes. Stop numbering sacraments.
Yes, please.
Latins. Come on.
Oh, I mean, it's okay if you need a number, it's fine. You know, all of these things that
take you from one mode, and of course marriage, you know, one mode of life to another mode
of life.
is to equip you to be faithful in this new way, right?
Because being married is a different kind of faithfulness
than the life of without a husband or a wife beforehand.
I mean, certainly the overall mode of faithfulness
is the same or the overall trajectory I should say,
is the same, but the mode has shifted a bit.
Now it's about serving Christ
by serving your husband or your wife
And then
God willing eventually serving those children, right?
That becomes the first place where you're supposed to love Christ
is with those people that are in your house.
So I mean, that's what I would say that marriage,
that the sacrament of marriage does
or the actual wedding service does.
Although it's an interesting question.
I had someone ask, I can't remember what the context was.
Someone asked me this recently, they say,
is the sacrament of marriage the service
or is it the whole life together?
and I loved to come.
response with yes. I mean, there's definitely something going on in that service. And that is
the transition, just like baptism as a transition and ordination as a transition, but then it has to
be lived out throughout the rest of life ever after. I don't know, what would you, what would you
want to add or um, actually or enrich or whatever? Well, just in terms of the relationship between
the two between the life and you know the wedding service. The thing that happens on that day.
What ultimately gives it meaning is the life that's lived after it.
Right.
So, if you're baptized and then never darken the doorstep of a church again, right?
And go out and live a life of sin and wickedness, it's not that the baptism didn't do anything.
I mean, the baptism will maybe stand up against you at the judgment, but like it's not doing
you any good, right?
thing with our nation if you are ordained and then proceed to be a wickedness.
and foul priest or deacon or bishop, right?
The story is, God's accretion is a bishop.
Didn't, you know, count except maybe against him.
And so the same thing, the same thing really
is true of the wedding itself.
What makes that meaningful what happens there,
in a positive sense, is the life that's a faithfulness
that's lived thereafter, right?
And if that doesn't follow from it.
then again, that wedding service may stand against us, right?
When we've been unfaithful to it.
But if we want it to be meaningful in the positive way,
if we want it to be promises that find fulfillment come
to fill up our lives, then it has to be joined with faithfulness
thereafter.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
All right, well, this next question comes to us from Carlean.
Hello, fathers.
This is Carleen.
calling from California.
I'm a recently-illumined new member of the Orthodox Church.
I came in with my family in March, so I'm pretty green.
So bear with me and give me a lots of grace
as I ask my question.
I wanted to know something about the traditions
of the church, one of the things I love about Orthodoxy
is that it is the bastion of the ancient faith
and that the church is right with tradition
and change if it comes, comes very slowly.
This gives me a great sense of security.
And I love.
the wisdom and weighted care with which the church approaches any shifts.
So can you talk to me a little bit about how do changes in the church occur?
How does something like St. John Christus Soms homling for a pasca become part of
what the church always does? How does St. Cassia Nis,
hymns move into something the church uses? How do the shifts like this occur?
and maybe you can give me kind of a zoom out view on.
realize the church does make tiny changes in shifts. So how do those happen and still respect
tradition and make sure that these are wise and careful changes? Thank you so much.
Well I love that question and it's a good one because you have this idea that some people have
that the Orthodox church never changes but of course that's just historically untenable.
Right, if they mean by that, we do things exactly the same way that we have always done them in every...
possible respect. That's just not a thing. But what's interesting is that there is also,
and she didn't mention this, but there's also this problem where people might acknowledge
historical change, but have the sense that that's over now. You know, that there is kind of some
point in the past at which, for instance, especially like liturgical change was completed.
And now, you know, there's no possibility for it after that, right?
And I think part of what's bound up in that is there's often this kind of reactivity,
a reactiveness, reactionaryness that a lot of folks have, especially in light of the
fact that the world is often chaotic and is addicted to innovation.
And so then they see the Orthodox Church and say, ah, here is the place where I am going
to be free of all of that.
Nice.
agree with that in the sense that the Orthodox tradition is not addicted to innovation.
But there is change and there is creativity and there continues to be creativity.
Like she mentioned the hem of Cassini, there was a point to which that was not written.
And then there was a point which St. Cassini wrote it and there was a point in which it
was probably just used in her monastery.
And then I mean, I don't know the history of that, the spread of that particular hymn,
it must have started.
local and then eventually spread, you know, there are hymns that the church uses in particular
and the liturgical practice that in many cases are maybe not even a century old, you know, some of
them are newer, right? There's certainly feast days that are new, you know, because there's a new
saint or other kinds of feast days sometimes are brought up. But I mean, she asked about the kind of
mechanism by which it happens.
Largely, it's...
Bishops...
making pastoral decisions that they feel that are appropriate.
Most of them are relatively minor, but sometimes there actually is liturgical reform on a moderately
large level.
We can think, for instance, of the Nikonian Church reforms in Russia, which are, we're
of course hugely controversial, but basically did stick.
I mean, that's essentially the form of Russian Orthodox liturgical life now, where those
Reform.
from several centuries ago, but even before that St. Philotheos Cook-Ginnellas, who is the
patriarch of Constantinople, who canonized St. Gregory Palomas, he was a liturgical reformer.
Now the kinds of reforms that they did were not some massive replacement of the liturgical
tradition, but there were still changes, right?
And of course we can think of canonical shifts that happened early on.
you see the screen.
There were some there was more variation probably than there is now.
And I think sometimes seeing those kinds of consensus is emerges,
what gives people the temptation to think that change stops in some cases.
I doubt there's going to be any changes in church canons,
but what happens if the church of Greece and the church of Russia get together and say,
hey, let's go ahead and have the same old Testament canon, even though they don't currently.
if they made that a-
if the Greek church said, okay, we'll take fourth,
Ezdrous, I don't think that would be a problem.
You know, but I mean,
so largely it's pastoral stuff like that.
It's ultimately enhanced the episcopacy.
This is their job.
They can be creative, they can bless creativity.
Sometimes you see changes happen
because one parish has a practice and another parish doesn't.
I think it's cool and they go ahead and adopt it.
And, you know, they find it meaningful and good, and then it spreads and it becomes a thing.
Right?
So, I don't know.
I mean, there's a lot of ways that it happens.
I would not say that it's always very tiny and incremental.
Because, like I said, there are sometimes programs of liturgical reform.
They're not usually, like on the level, frankly, of that we saw in the post-Vaticantoo era
in the Roman Catholic Church.
Almost never.
I mean, I'm not a liturgical historian.
but from the liturgical history that I know, you don't see that level of change in the Orthodox church.
So, but there are, there are sometimes fairly systemic changes that do occur and
the question then often is, well, how does that get received? Is it just rejected?
Does it become incorporated to the life of the church and sometimes it does? I don't know,
Father, what do you want to add to all that? Yeah, I mean, I think the key thing is that
What we're talking about, what we're talking about, the truth is we're talking about Christ
himself, right?
It's a person who is the same yesterday, today, and forever.
And we're talking about faithfulness to him.
So the question that's not just like once a generation, but continually asked and is the
task again.
really of the bishops is what does it look like to follow Christ for these people at this
time in this place?
And in the broad contours, that's not going to change.
So it's not like, well now I think murder should be okay.
That's not going to forget that whole one husband, one wife, marriage thing.
cut us
stuff. Yeah, it is not going to change. Right, right? Right and wrong is not going to change.
We're not going to start putting stake on the altar. Right, right. So I mean, the broad
contrast is that this is going to change. But I mean, people living in a gray and world,
in the 13th century and people living in an urban environment in the 21st century have very
There you go.
ways of life to start with. So there are going to be differences in their family
structures. There are going to be differences in the relationship to their work
and those kind of things. And so the same faithfulness to Christ is going to
take subtly different shapes. When your work is spending 14 hours a day working
your family, farm to feed your family, or if it's going in
punching a clock and working in a cubicle farm and then coming home to be faced with various
entertainment options.
It's not going to be radically different.
There's not going to be things that are horribly simple for one and that are the road to
theosis for the other.
But there also not going to be identical.
That's what's sort of continually being asked and continually there are adjustments being
made.
continually there are and things being
tried because every bishop is also not infallible, right?
No bishop is infallible.
And so sometimes they're gonna say,
hey, this seems like a way we could go
and then that's gonna have unintended consequences
in the life of the church.
And they're gonna draw back from that, right?
Or sometimes something one bishop does and tries,
the other bishops will say,
I don't know if that's a good idea and it won't spread
or other times other bishops will look at and say,
that seems to be work.
working well for the people of that local church, we should give that a try as well, or we
should try a slightly different version of that.
So that's sort of how these things happen because you can't just, to every culture, to every
time, to every place, just come up with a list of rules, just do these things.
you will find salvation.
And that's because, you know, crisis and carnage.
Right.
And history is real.
Yes.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay, well this next one comes from Moses,
and I think this is a tough one.
Hello, fathers.
My name is Moses Reese.
I'm from Portland, Oregon.
I have a question about the body in gender.
In your episode, God's body,
you define the body as an excess of potentialities
in the recent episode, Prophet Motive.
There's some references made to individual
will be accessing spiritual forces from...
the liminal between gender state, or sometimes being thrust out of a gender state as a result of
exposure to spiritual forces. In my work as a professional counselor, I've sometimes talked with
trends and non-binary individuals who describe the experience of their internal sense of gender
being incongruent with their body to some degree, they describe grabbing energy, craving
into different sort of body, and this incongruence can be milder extreme, but centers on how the
the experience of bodies. So then what is the potentiality of a male body?
versus female body.
And is it strictly or primarily reproduction or is there more?
What is the essential nature of man or woman?
Is the essential nature of man or woman
that they have particular genitalia?
Or is the essence of manhood or woman
had something deeper and intangible?
And if the essence of gender is in fact
connected to particular genitals,
then what does that say about the overall nature of a person?
Is our essential nature bound up in organs
of elimination and reproduction?
And is this possibly reductionistic?
more so if the essence of the man had
humanhood is bound up in the genitalia, then what does this say about the nature of God?
On the other hand, if the essence of gender is not specifically tied to physical genitalia
for rather something internal and herentrend sending physical flesh, then what is actually
problematic about a trans or non-binary person's experience, journey and physical authorizations
to the body?
That's my question.
Thanks so much for the show.
It makes being a Christian a whole lot more fun.
Peace.
Okay, well...
Yeah, I think this is a tough one because there's so many potential mind fields and pitfalls
that can go along with it.
And I think often, and I appreciate the spirit with which Moses, you asked this question
because you're concerned about the care of people, whereas a lot of times when people
ask questions related to now this very very
a very hot question of gender.
It's about justifying, frankly, sexual immorality or all kinds of other very problematic behaviors.
I mean, we've talked many times on this show about this question of identity becoming,
you know, like one's personal identity, like I'm different from everybody else for the
following list of reasons that together make me unique.
a very problematic way to live. And that at least is some of the way that I think about this stuff.
But I'll be honest, I don't have a lot of really big, formed thoughts about how to understand this.
I have very clear thoughts about the right kinds of behavior.
But I don't yet have fully worked out ideas about
and that's really how we get there. So, Father.
I'm just gonna keep it over you and I wanna hear what you have to say about this.
Yes.
So, yeah, this is not a question of Father Andrew being chickened to really delve into this.
It is that he does not share my reckless abandon.
Because I'm about to get everybody mad at me.
We'll see if this actually makes it out onto the X-Face Airwaves and you list the
into it and I have not made you mad in any way send an email. I'll be curious to see if there's
anyone out there. So yeah so part of again we have to start by interrogating the question a little
because as we said before sort of the way you started inquiry is going to shape the results you get.
Yeah, and so there's something that happened right there were reports
distinctions that were made in the late mid-20th century that have kind of been lost now and are part
of what's causing a lot of this confusion. And one of the big ones, and here's where I'm going to
take off a bunch of people right off the bat, is that there's a difference between biological sex
and gender, right, that those aren't the same thing.
So biological sex, right, is all organisms.
right, if you're into the evolution thing and humans are higher primates, right? They come into biological sexes.
Male and female. There are also intersex people for various reasons, genetic issues, other things.
There are people who physiologically don't conform to one of those two.
Those are people who have their own set of issues.
they face and struggles they face.
And I frankly find it kind of offensive when they're used as like a political football
in these arguments.
So the existence of intersex people literally has nothing to do with transgenderism.
Because this is a question of biological sex and transgenderism is about gender, which
is a different thing.
So respectfully out of respect.
then we need to leave them out of the rest of this discussion.
Right? And when those people are in our churches and that kind of thing, we need to treat them
with respect and help them with the struggles the same way we would anyone else. Right?
But so that's a separate kind of issue.
So gender then, right? And part of this gets confused too because we're speaking English.
it in.
pretty much every other ant language I've ever studied. Language has gender.
So different words are masculine and feminine. It has nothing to do with biology.
What's the word? And there's even people don't think tables are women.
Yeah, there's even neutral gender. And I think some languages have more than three actually.
grammatical render, you know. Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
English doesn't have it and so that makes pronouns radioactive now because that's the only part of the
English language that's really gendered as pronouns. And we've all forgotten that we used to call
ships sheep. But so, again, language gender is not related to this. So it's commonly called
gender in these discussions is basically this
I'm going to use another word.
It's going to make another group of people mad at me.
It's a social construct.
Meaning it's something that is constructed by a society in terms of this is the way males
should dress, present themselves, speak, appear in public.
And this is the way females should dress, present themselves in public.
And obviously that's different in different cultures and different talks.
Like most of the earth's history
mended not where slacks or pants or jeans, right?
That's now we consider masculine attire.
Mended where that for most of human history, right?
If you saw someone dressed as Louis the 15th,
you would not say there is a hyper masculine person, right?
So that has changed, right?
The bounty bothers the United States.
and stockings right and
I heal shoes.
Rendo do that anymore.
In our current cultural conception of gender.
So there are people who are men or women biologically,
who at any given point don't feel comfortable with the way
their society tells them they should dress and act
and present themselves.
We didn't use to make...
a big deal out of this. Lots of women were Tom Boys in some period of their growing up,
right? And they liked things that our culture associated with boys. They liked sports or
they liked playing with what we considered to be boys toys. Not a big deal. They didn't
make them a boy. They didn't make them a man. Why? Well, because that's just social
construct. There's nothing to do with biology. Right? We were very clear this verse in its
biologically this, right?
They have
to like some things that in our society are more commonly liked by the other sex.
So the other in terms of ground clearing, the other issue here, and this even came out
in the question a little bit, is that, and the questioner at least sounded like, you
know, we're not allowed to assume anymore, but sounded like a man.
And so he talked about genitalia.
For men, it's very easy to talk about reproduction in terms of genitalia, because that's how men
are involved in reproduction.
But for a woman, most of what's involved in reproduction is carrying a new human being
in their womb for nine months.
So the reproductive structures of the body, especially if we...
as best I can because I'm not one, look at it from a woman's perspective, is much more
involved than just their organs of reproduction and elimination.
There is more involved here.
And that's not sort of the end of physiological differences between men and women.
And so when we say that a body is a collection of potentialities and power.
Right? So obviously there are some of those that are different. Right? A big, glaringly,
obvious one is that men don't have wounds. Right? They can't conceive and carry a child
for nine months. Right? That's a potentiality. That's a power that they do not possess.
And that women do possess. Again, that doesn't mean that every woman possesses it because
we're in a fallen world where there are disorders of the body, right? Just as there are disorders
to the soul, there's disease, there are problems.
where things don't work, but the structures, the physiological structures are aimed at
that possessed by women and not by men.
We've also said and tried to make clear that your soul is not a thing separate from your
body.
Your soul is the life that is in your body.
You are your body, the resurrection is physical.
the resurrection Christ is still a man.
His body is still a male body, a male human body.
So, that is our physical structures are not sort of ancillary.
We have to get past, this is a play-doh brain thing, that our real self is this spherical
thing inhabiting our body and our body is coincidental.
We are our body just as much as we are our soul.
Yeah, I feel like there's a Cartesian backing to a lot of this question, right?
You know, right, right. And so in order for the transgender narrative to function,
right, you have to take gender and make it not a social construct and make it real.
You have to say if this person is
is biologically male, but they like sheer a better than he man.
So they're actually a girl or a woman.
Meaning there is something essential about this cartoon as opposed to that cartoon.
Right?
There's something in it.
And so you have to essentialize these things in a way that just does not work.
Right?
but just does not work.
That would be to say George Washington was secretly a feminine because
Dressing wearing high heels and stockings at a wig is feminine no matter what
Right and and and make some a female so that that doesn't work
so when we're we're talking to someone who identifies as trans
This is a person we should hate. This is a person who's confused right and
And part of the reason, frankly, that they've gotten confused is
are modern sense of identity and we have a whole generation of people now, really two
generations of people now, whose first sexual experiences, whose only experiences of community
have taken place on the internet, meaning their disembodied.
And we haven't taken into account what having all of a person's sexual experiences be disembodied
does to a person.
first developing their concept of sexuality and identity. But we're seeing it play out,
right? Because if you don't form your sense of identity in community, right, then your
identity, if you're just talking about yourself as a black hole, you end up in nihilism. Because
by ourselves, we aren't human, we aren't anything. Aristotle do that, right? If you're
You're going to live by yourself.
You have to be a beast or a god.
And he just said, poor Kate Noelle's dose, but you can't be human by yourself.
Right.
So the solution to this is not to degrade people and insult people, insist on calling them
things they don't want to be called in public to make some kind of point.
Right.
That's not the solution.
solution is we have to work to rebuild community.
So that people who have grown up without any concept of what it even is start to understand
what community life is.
And once you're in a community, your identity gets formed because you have a role within
that community.
You have gifts and abilities that you share with that community.
And then in return, the community places certain responsibilities upon you.
And you contributing what you can and fulfilling those responsibilities gives you a sense
of self and a sense of self.
worth and a sense of being appreciated and that makes for a healthy person. But we can't
argue out people out of this while they're sitting alone in their room in front of a computer.
No matter what you post on Twitter, you're not going to convince anybody of anything and
you're not going to help them. And I know most of the people doing these things don't care
about helping them because they've identified these people as the enemy. Then some kind of
culture war. Right.
But our goal is Christians should be to help these people find salvation and they're only going to find salvation in a community
Specifically the community of the church and that's why that's where we start building
Yeah, so there now everyone's mad at me. I don't know. I'm happy
Actually, I'm good with all of that. Oh
Yeah, I know I know you can answer the hate bail then. Oh, yeah, I will
You know, I
I have to be careful how I say this.
But I've had experience with a young person, so a teenager who, it's like you said, this
person was raised basically in front of a screen and came to say, I'm not the actual
sex that I was born, I'm the other one.
And I thought about, you know, I looked at that person's life and I thought about, well,
okay.
So in this case, it was a girl who said that she was a boy.
And I thought about, I looked at her life and I thought, well, she's never had a dad.
Dad was out of the picture from a very early age.
and has been at home for either in public schools
where a lot of those things are,
let's be honest, a lot of public schools these days
are totally happy with if someone says
that kind of thing to say, okay,
we will help you and support you to be that way
and to help you go down that path
as far as you wanna go, that's just reality.
And not getting anything different at home.
and
Just sort of realizing like, okay, this person actually doesn't even know what a man is,
and they think she is one, but there's nothing manly about her.
Like literally, there's nothing man, not even this kind of gender stereotyping stuff, right?
It was just sort of like an identification, like a switch was flipped.
It's not like she started dressing differently or anything like that.
I think you're right. I mean from my experience there.
There's the result of the fragmentation of the breakdown of human communities.
And the place of sanity has to be the church.
And like you said, that sanity is not simply giving people lectures about how they're
wrong about stuff, but actually creating a community that they can plug into and enter
into that web of relationships where who they are as God created them to be is meaningful.
is something that they can actually...
to connect to because in many cases they haven't been able.
And I'm sure there's a lot of different kinds of experiences.
The one that I happen to have interacted with this young lady is not universal.
I know.
But the cure for this kind of stuff is a scene community where someone can plug
into that and be part of it.
It's always an isolation that we often, a nice isolation, I should say,
that we really really go off the deep end and then get in.
in dangerous waters. So, all right. Well, I hope that's helpful to you, Moses, in your work.
Okay. So this next one comes from our friend Kyle from Ireland. He is called into the show
and multiplications.
Hi, fathers. My question is about the second coming. Is this, is the second coming of Christ
an event which will happen in material time at some point in the future? Or is it something
which happens on an individual.
level in one's personal experience during one's life, meaning that the second
coming of Christ has already happened for some people throughout history, or is
it a way of describing what happens to everyone when they die, so they enter into
judgment or the second coming of Christ? Or is it all of these? Or is it none of
this.
Anyway, thank you very much.
All right, it's a good question.
So how about a father?
What exactly is as he put it the second coming?
I know you don't like that phrase actually.
Yes.
Well, yeah, because as I said before, it's kind of deceptive.
We're not that far as we record at least.
We're not that far past the ascension.
And yeah, fighting back against the idea that Jesus went away somewhere.
went away somewhere.
Right.
Therefore, it's coming back.
And so second coming in return, kind of give that.
It's not that they're horrible translations, just they give it connotation.
So there's other language from the Bible like Christ's glory appearing or just when he
appears that I think conveys the idea that he is still very much with us in our midst.
Right.
Yeah, we got sort of.
directly. He'll be manifest in a way that he isn't right now. Right, right to us. Yeah, yeah. So,
yes, there is going to be an end of material time or there's going to be an end of this age,
right? And what time will be like in the age to come? We don't know.
And by what it will be like, I mean how we will experience it.
Right.
action, we don't know. Likewise, how time is experienced when someone is separated from
their body, we don't know. So I can't answer at least at this point what that's like,
right? Whether they experience it as waiting for a long time or you know what I mean,
whether the intermediate state is experienced as it is.
extension of time or not, right? That's the only way we can talk. Yeah. Right?
Is in terms of time and space, but that I would, I would suggest at the very least would
apply differently to someone who is not in a body, right or not in body, with a material
body. But what that means, I can't say, right?
Yeah. So if you ask the question has someone experienced it already, right, I can answer that
no because the already means from our perspective. Yeah. Not from their perspective.
I could say from our perspective, the last judgment hasn't happened.
That's why we continue to pray for the department among other reasons. Right.
But I can't answer from their perspective. Yeah, we can't project ourselves. I mean,
And this is the bad thing again.
right? We can't predict ourselves out there and say, ah, yes, I know what it's like to
be departed from this life. And I know I could tell you, I'm here at the second coming and we're
looking forward to you joining us like we don't know that. Right. Right. And even to phrase the question,
right? What is this person who is departed doing right now? Well, the now is now time from my
perspective right yeah
So now for me and now for them might mean
to completely different things.
So.
Right.
So yeah, that's probably unsatisfactory.
But it's OK.
That's what we got.
Kyle from Ireland always asks good questions.
So it was a good one though.
OK.
All right.
Well, we got a couple more.
And this one is from Phil.
Hello, fathers.
My name is Phil.
I'm up in Canada.
Thank you for such a great...
show. I absolutely love it. God continue to strengthen you in your great work. I'm also really
thankful that I get to speak playpin and send a question. So my question is as follows.
And second Corinthians 2 14 to 15, we read that Christ's work on the cross, quote,
cancelled the bond which stood against us with its legal demands. This he set aside,
kneeling it to the cross. He disarmed the principalities and powers and made a public example of them
triumphant over them in him and thought.
In this passage we not only see what we talk about often on the show, that is that Christ
put the beat down on the devils, but also that salvation is not just healing, it is a
debt.
It might even be called a legal vision of salvation.
I bring this passage to your attention because often in Orthodox circles we see salvation
as healing.
Talk of salvation as debt or other legal terms is usually derogatory, they refer to as Catholic
or Protestant.
the above passage illustrates though there is something clearly
more going on. I know that on the show we've talked about justice as being setting things
in their right order. And I can see how this is related to healing, example, pleasing
bones back in their joints. But I'm not sure how to make more sense of the passage than
that. So my question is, is there a more authentically orthodox version of salvation
as a legal concept? Can you please just riff on this idea? Thank you.
Okay, it's a good question. I'm gonna guess. Yeah, go ahead. He's from
Manitoba. Oh based on his accent maybe Winnipeg. Yeah, he has the same accent as Chris Jericho.
Wow. That's what I'm going by. Wow, that's, that's fun. Who is, you know, someone, someone tell me
if I'm right. That's some leader point. We just learned a little bit about your interest in
Canadian American wrestling. Yeah, well, and here's the thing. Here's the thing. I'm going,
I'm maybe looking to go on all Henry Higgins about Canada.
which would be a weird, whole weird thing, right?
Okay.
All right. Um, so yeah, um, I'm not sure that I throw you off completely.
Yeah, right. Exactly.
We were.
Are we? Yeah. Yeah.
I, I, so he said second Corinthians 2, 14 and 15, but I think he might be
quoting something else.
I'm not sure though.
That's the handwriting of our sins.
Yeah.
Right, right, right, right, so
Yeah, because that's not what's there in that passage.
But in any event, that's in collotions as well.
He was, yeah.
Clotions too?
Yeah.
I think that's what he's looking at.
So anyway.
I knew what passage you would start.
Yeah, no, I mean, I knew it.
I was just like, I don't think that that's right.
But yes, there's a reference to indebtedness and this sort of handwriting and, you know,
That's it.
I'm looking at the net Bible, for instance, now refers to a certificate of indebtedness expressed in decrees opposed to us.
Second Corinthians 2.14.
Yeah, which is very legal kind of language, financial kind of language.
Those are two different things though.
That's true, right?
That's part of the problem with the question is that debt and legal are two different things.
Two different things.
Yeah, I mean, we tend to in our modern experience,
they, you know, debt is a very legal experience.
Well, we don't have debtors' prisons anymore.
That's, I mean, that's true.
I suppose.
But, you know, the law can get involved based on your, you know,
and there's contracts that you signed.
You can get a judgment, you can get a judgment
against you in a civil court.
Right.
Maybe.
But also, like, if you sign a contract, that has legal force.
That's enforceable, right?
It becomes force of law.
You know.
and indebtedness is a contract that you sign.
So, that kind of stuff is there,
but I think, I mean,
the way that I read this that makes the most sense to me
is that, you know, debt is so much bound,
I mean, you may have made mention of debtors' prisons,
but I mean debt is so much bound up,
especially in the Roman Empire
with the institution of slavery
that, which is another very, very common image
using the new Testament for.
our relationship to sin, right, that it's slavery, and it's slavery to demonic powers, which
is of course the reference in verse 15, right, disarming the rulers and authorities,
he has made a public disgrace to them, trapping over them by the cross.
And so then this indebtedness that we have for Christ to pay that debt or to tear up the
the debt as it is in this particular passage.
Nailing it to the cross, right, is to really
Jesus from that slavery, you know, that's gone that way.
And I mean, my take is that like legal language and, you know, indebtedness language, whether
they're bound up together or not, like that stuff is in scripture.
The question, and I, you know, he made mention of how a lot of Orthodox people will say,
no salvation is healing, it has nothing to do with this sort of other kind of language.
But I think that that's a problem that when Orthodox people talk that way, it's a problem
because
It's throwing out some biblical language in favor of other biblical language, which is the problem with the other side of the question that says no, it's primarily a legal issue is it's throwing out other biblical language in favor of that biblical language.
And so you get this truncated view either way, right.
I think you're trying to be overly charitable.
Oh, okay.
Since this is an episode where you've decided to use your go ahead and make everybody angry so go ahead, you know, yes, yeah
We're again, reckless abandon.
No.
So, and I can tell from your answer that you read this action related to this passage in
religion of the apostles.
Anyway.
Everyone buy it at storedunhidfade.com.
So yeah.
So there are a couple things with interrogating the question, right?
First of all, at least on this show we've ever said that salvation is primarily healing.
No, we know
We have let alone only healing.
I haven't even said primarily.
Yeah, that's way down the check.
Right?
So being set free from bodyless powers,
being raised from the dead,
and being purified from sin and its effects.
Right?
Right.
That's what we talk about salvation being on this show.
Now the purification of sin and its effects,
healing covers part of that.
But when we talk about atonement,
the purification from Senate.
its effects is so that we can be filled with the Holy Spirit with the presence of God.
It's the beginning of theosis and transformation, right, in a positive sense, not just healing,
right? So yeah, all of that is way watered down. So it answered to the final form of the question,
well yeah, it's a lot more than healing, and that's what Paul has said.
But yeah, and then the other thing with this wiggle between debt and legal, right?
So...
I'm going to assume this is positively motivated.
I know there's a certain mindset that says, hey, we need to throw our western brothers
of bow, right?
Brothers and sisters, right?
And we've got Western right Orthodox people, some of them are friends of mine.
And sometimes they feel the need because they're using Western liturgical usages to also try
to defend bits and bobs of Western theology unless it's real.
So we wanted
try to throw people a bone. And so using a legal is sort of this broad category that covers
12 things that we could say, well, yeah, we think there's some legal imagery there. Now
by legal, we need something totally different than what say, penal substitution area, tone
meant or satisfaction theory means. But it's still legal so we can be friendly. And to
be that's that's just paper papering over actual differences right so as you
mentioned that the word
there in Greek actually refers to a promissory note.
Right.
And this is connected to St. Paul's common imagery,
Wages of Sin is Death.
Right?
So we have brought this upon ourselves.
Again, it's not a death penalty.
Right?
And that's proved by the way St. Paul elsewhere in Romans
uses the term Wages.
Right?
He said, if salvation was Wages, it would not be grace.
mean the work of God, it would be something you earn, right? So when he says the wages of sin is
death, that means death is something we earn, not the action of God apart from our own actions,
meaning it's not a death penalty. St. Paul's straight says that, okay? So this is, and if you read
Hebrews, which is at least Pauline, even if you don't want to call it St. Paul's epistle
to the Hebrews, which I'm comfortable doing, but even if you're not, it's at least Pauline.
It talks about how
We, through the fear of death, have been enslaved our whole lives by the devil who holds the power of death who Christ came into faith.
So as you said, this is about freedom from slavery to sin and death, which Christ accomplishes on our behalf.
And that's not, again, a legal matter.
It's not that there's a court case between the devil and Christ and Christ's life.
wins the civil case and therefore becomes the holder of our dad and tears it right?
That's not the imagery that's being used.
The imagery is cry saving us from the consequences of our actions which we've
originally earned. But that are part of the natural consequence of what happens
when we give ourselves over to sin and rebellion and follow the demons.
So.
Like, I don't, I just don't feel the need to find a way to agree with Anselm.
I don't feel the need to find a way to partially agree with John Calvin about penal substitutionary
at Oldman.
I just don't.
I don't need to.
Be free.
Yes.
And I'm sorry if that upsets people who do agree with them.
I don't see any positive.
to it. Yeah, I mean, we don't, we don't need to, like, we don't need to be there. I mean,
just to put it bluntly, they're not orthodox saints. So like, we don't need to figure out
how to incorporate them into what we're doing. Yeah. So it's not serving a purpose for us.
It's not answering a question that we don't have an answer to otherwise. Like, yeah. Yeah.
It's just, I mean, it's to be, it's like the lamest kind of ecumenism, like, just like,
Okay, let's pretend we're...
We agree more than we do.
You know, that's good.
Why?
All right, so on that note we have one more question.
This comes from Jonathan.
Hey podfathers, my name is Jonathan Harris.
And I just recently joined the podcast and the Facebook group.
And I ended up asking a question the other day about
ancient Near Eastern cosmology and what you guys believe
about that.
Do you agree with a scholarship of the day
that sees it.
3, 2, 1.
cosmology with a with a hard sky and all of that stuff for do you disagree and if you do agree
what do you think that means for inspiration and biblical inspiration and and how we read the Bible and understand it and all
of that stuff that's been really on my mind lately so it'd be great if you guys could speak to that a little more in depth
but thank you so much for the podcast and really enjoy it.
Alright, thank you. I feel like I heard...
Seagulls in the background of his recording there.
So he's coming to us from the beach.
I don't know.
Yeah.
Or he's going to be headrun and they're about to attack.
So yeah, actually, I want us eventually to do a whole episode about this question, about
cosmology.
Oh, I thought you were going to say the birds.
No.
Okay, yeah.
No, that's a much better.
Not the birds.
No, I can't handle even mild horror films like that.
I can't do it.
I'm just...
to total pansy in that regard.
Yeah, so I guess like the way that I would sort of
restate his question would be, okay, it seems in the Bible the cosmology that's presented
is got three levels, you've got the heavens above us, you've got the earth that we live
on and you've got the underworld underneath us.
I should point out by the way that the middle part is referred to as middle earth in pre-modern
Germanic literature just putting that out there.
Mid-end-yattered.
But, and then now we've got, you know, we live long after Copernicus and all that kind of stuff,
and we know that that's not the way that things are shaped.
Do we actually believe that that's what's presented in the Bible, if that really is the case,
then what do we do with that?
The fact that we know now that that's not how the world is actually arranged.
So here's my understanding of that.
My.
understanding is that you actually do in some cases in the ancient world you get people
who seem to hold to more than one cosmology at a time. On the one hand, they will say
the earth is round, which a lot of them had figured out with the use of geometry. They
could tell that the earth was round. And then at the same time, also describe the earth
in three tier cosmological terms, which suggests that
they didn't see them as contradictory models, that they're essentially describing two different
sets of experiences that are related to the same reality, but are two different ways of kind of
talking about it. But it's also my understanding that you do get at various points in time, certain people
who very much push a kind of a total even materialization of the three-tier version of cosmology.
and say, this is the way that the world simply is laid out.
For my part, I have no problem believing in both at the same time,
that the three-tier cosmology describes something like what we would describe as a spiritual experience.
And it's not about an empirical material measurement.
And then you can take an empirical material measurement and see you know planets that are basically spheres.
going around the sun, which is itself part of a galaxy and all that kind of thing, and
that both are meaningful models and both apply, right?
Both apply to actual phenomenological experiences that people have.
I know, that's my understanding of it.
And I would say that even if it is the case that the Bible teaches only a three-tier cosmology,
and I have to say, I have to defer to you on this, whether that's all that's said there,
bother but
Even if it does teach that, I don't see that that's a problem for believing that the Bible is inspired,
because the Bible isn't trying to answer material, empirical questions about planets and astronomy and so forth.
That's not what its purpose is.
Instead, it's talking about the actual experiences that people have and their experience of God within that and of the world and so forth.
So that's my set of thoughts that I have about this.
So there's a bunch of things that make this complicated.
One of them is the concept of spiritual geography that we've talked about before.
Right.
So, with Leviathan, Swallows, Jonah, swims down beneath the pillars of the earth, like
no one was claiming there are actually pillars that are supported by nothing, supporting
the earth.
Right.
That's sacred geography, how those things, how those things that overlap though with
real geography or material geography I should say.
So there's not that complicates it.
There's also, as we talked about in the how-to and how not to read the Bible episode, the
fact that the Bible does not make scientific claims ever at all.
So trying to read it from the perspective of modern science is fundamentally caddy
want this right and that's not saying science is bad right go do
science, right? But like, if what you're really into studying is ancient textiles, great,
go get your PhD in history, study ancient textiles. But if you try to read the Bible from the perspective
of textiles, right? Like, you might have some interesting insights here and there, you know,
be willing to hear. But on the whole, you're not really going to get the thrust of what the Bible
wants to teach you. Right? And so the same thing, if you try to read the Bible from the
perspective of astrophysics. You might have some interesting insights here and there, but
you're not going to get the for us because it's not making claims from that perspective. That's
not the discourse that's taking place in scripture. And then of course, there's what
But when you expect God to say to Bronze Age people, right?
So, we all have a little bit of 19th century German in us where we have this assumption
that we stand at the pinnacle of history and that includes science.
So we've got this all or pretty much all locked down, right, in terms of science.
And so, if God were really going to speak, he'd communicate in our scientific terms because
we're at the pinnacle of human history, right?
And so the fact that he talks to these broadsage people about
the world as if it's the way those Bronze Age people thought it was. That's a
problem. The reality is if God actually explained the world to Bronze Age people the way it actually
is, we still wouldn't understand it. Because if there's a humanity in this age 2000 years from now,
we will probably look at today's science like we were a bunch of idiots. The way modern people look
at, you know, the evil science and alchemy.
There will be all kinds of things that we think are horrific and stupid about our current
science.
So, that whole chain of argument is based on this sort of modernist hubris and doesn't
hold up and make a lot of sense.
So, the reality is God had things that he wanted to communicate to Bronze Age people,
So he spoke to them in a language that existed at the time.
And in ways using metaph-
and descriptions that they would understand so that he could convey to them what you wanted to convey.
Yeah, and it's still meaningful for us. Even though like those models are still meaningful for us,
even if they're not what our scientific textbooks are talking about.
Right, and our current models will seem equally quaint.
Yeah. Right. In a thousand years, right, to the people of that time.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, so all right.
Well, that wraps up this big Q&A episode.
Thank you very much for listening everyone.
If you didn't get to catch us live in one of our previous episodes in the future,
we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpirits at AncientFate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page.
Or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakBife.com slash LordOfSpirits.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
the month at 7 p.m. Eastern or P.M. Pacific except like not.
today. So like the next actual live one will be like the second week of July.
Second Thursday. And if you are on Facebook you can like our page, join our
discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere but most importantly
please share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it or even
someone is kind of, yeah, about it. And finally be sure to go to
AncientPath.com Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of other hit
hard pod casters. I'm gonna go ahead and say all of the things.
Stay on the air.
Thank you, goodnight and God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.